<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Jerubbaal justified: or, A plain rebuke of the high (pretended humble) remonstrance and plea against Mr. Crofton his reformation not separation or, a plea for communion with the church under those corruptions, and by that disorderly ministration, to which he cannot conform, nor by it administer.  Demonstrating, T.P. (alias D.) his grosse mistakes of Mr. Crofton his principle and argument: as also the fallacie and vanity of his pleaded necessity for his (confessed) separation from publique assemblies, which is found insufficient to acquit him of schisme.  To which is added a position, disputing the lawfulnesse of ministers receiving an imposed liturgy.</title>
            <author>R. S.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1663</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 126 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 27 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A58653</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC"> 297426168</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S130</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">297426168</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocn 297426168</idno>
            <idno type="VID">100906</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A58653)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 100906)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 1046:5, 2925:1)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Jerubbaal justified: or, A plain rebuke of the high (pretended humble) remonstrance and plea against Mr. Crofton his reformation not separation or, a plea for communion with the church under those corruptions, and by that disorderly ministration, to which he cannot conform, nor by it administer.  Demonstrating, T.P. (alias D.) his grosse mistakes of Mr. Crofton his principle and argument: as also the fallacie and vanity of his pleaded necessity for his (confessed) separation from publique assemblies, which is found insufficient to acquit him of schisme.  To which is added a position, disputing the lawfulnesse of ministers receiving an imposed liturgy.</title>
                  <author>R. S.</author>
                  <author>Crofton, Zachary, 1625 or 6-1672. Reformation not separation.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 43, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>printed in the year, 1663.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A reply to Crofton's Reformation not separation.</note>
                  <note>This is a replacement for incomplete S130 on reel 1046.  Cf.  Wing (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of originals in: Union Theological Seminary (New York, N.Y.). Library (reel 1046:5) and Folger Shakespeare Library (reel 2925:1).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Apologetic works --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Dissenters, Religious --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:100906:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:100906:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Jerubbaal Juſtified: Or, A Plain REBUKE OF THE High (pretended humble) Remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrance and Plea againſt Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> HIS <hi>Reformation</hi> not <hi>Separation:</hi> OR, A Plea for Communion with the Church under thoſe Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions, and by that diſorderly Miniſtration, to which he cannot Conform, nor by it Adminiſter.</p>
            <p>DEMONSTRATING, <hi>T. P.</hi> (alias <hi>D.</hi>) his groſſe miſtakes of Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> his Principle and Argument: as alſo the fallacie and vanity of his pleaded neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity for his (confeſſed) ſeparation from publique Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies, which is found inſufficient to acquit him of Schiſme.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>To which is added</hi> A Poſition, diſputing the lawfulneſſe of Miniſters receiving an impoſed Liturgy.</p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed in the Year, 1663.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:100906:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:100906:2"/>
            <head>TO THE PIOUS AFFECTIONATE READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Chriſtian Reader.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Hake off <hi>prejudice,</hi> abate <hi>affection,</hi> give place to <hi>judgement;</hi> let not the Chriſtian deſtroy the man, nor grace (captivating Reaſons dictates) dethrone the <hi>rational power;</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the <hi>object</hi> before you embrace or refuſe it; know well the <hi>nature of the Act</hi> before you do, or decline it; prove, hold faſt, or reject: Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures are eaſie and common, but when groundleſs, they become <hi>Calumnies,</hi> and retort with ſadneſs on the Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurers head; leaving him under the guilt of falſe judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>calling good evil, and evil good;</hi> condemning the juſt, and clouding the teſtimony to the truth; robbing God of the honour, and truth of the ſtrength of his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants Martyrdom.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:100906:3"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Reformation,</hi> The <hi>perfection of reformation</hi> is the work, the conteſt of our land and age: I muſt bear many witneſs, they have a <hi>zeal,</hi> but not <hi>according to knowledge;</hi> their affections flye after that which for want of knowledge, they do not, will not <hi>regularly follow;</hi> we eaſily hear what they would have, and what is taken from them; but can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not make them hear <hi>how</hi> they muſt have it, and how they muſt wait in <hi>their places</hi> until they can have it; and reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver what is removed.</p>
            <p>Reformation hath ever failed between <hi>Sylla</hi> and <hi>Charib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dis,</hi> and in theſe laſt days been moſt ſadly battered, and is almoſt ſplit on the Rocks of <hi>ſuperſtition</hi> and <hi>ſeparation:</hi> theſe Rocks are <hi>viſible,</hi> but the courſe to paſs between them without daſhing on either, is <hi>dark and difficult,</hi> and the Devil laboureth to daſh us ſomtimes on the one, ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times on the other; in one he acts like himſelf, in the other like an <hi>Angel of light;</hi> and thoſe lights which ſhould in this ſtreight direct us, are taken down, and in this caſe did, and do give ſo dim and uncertain light, that it is a mirror of mercy that any eſcape <hi>Shipwrack,</hi> what cauſe have we to priſe any who herein advance them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and ſhine brightly though thereby they expoſe themſelves to the tempeſtuous aſſaults and boiſtrous blaſts of men devoted to either extream.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Crofton,</hi> as <hi>Luther</hi> conteſting againſt the <hi>Pope,</hi> and at the ſame time the <hi>Anabaptiſts,</hi> for <hi>firſt degrees of Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation;</hi> and as <hi>Cartwright</hi> and others againſt <hi>Prelates</hi> and <hi>Separating Browniſts</hi> for <hi>further degrees of Reformation;</hi> hath expoſed himſelf to, and been afflicted by men of both extreams; and not a little <hi>wounded in the houſe of his friends,</hi> who are become his Enemies <hi>becauſe he told them the truth;</hi> many have cenſured, calumniated him, who cannot reſiſt the <hi>wiſdom and Spirit by which he hath ſpoken.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yet rather then truth ſhall want <hi>contradiction,</hi> or error
<pb facs="tcp:100906:3"/> ſcribe by ſilence, Satan will find and ſtir up inſtruments among <hi>Gods Servants,</hi> who ſhall ſharpen the old weapons of moſt bitter enemies, whereby to aſſault the aſſertors of truth, and ſay ſomething; that ſimple ſouls may be deluded, (<hi>with a Mr.</hi> Crofton <hi>is anſwered</hi>) though not one word is ſaid to purpoſe; nor one Argument urged by Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> is at all anſwered.</p>
            <p>If he be (as I dare affirm he is) a <hi>Son in Presbytery</hi> who hath lifted up the heel againſt his Father, let me aſſure thee Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> inſtead of adjudging him to <hi>Chams curſe,</hi> will pray he may <hi>dwell in the Tents of Shem,</hi> he having diſcovered <hi>his own,</hi> not any thing of his <hi>Fathers nakedneſs,</hi> onely when its ſaid a <hi>Presbyter,</hi> and <hi>Scotch Presbyter</hi> hath <hi>anſwered Mr.</hi> Croftons <hi>Plea againſt Separation;</hi> and that by onely urging the old uncharitable Plea of the moſt rigid Separatiſts (viz.) <hi>God is not worſhipped by the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgy, the Miniſtration by the Liturgy is poyſon,</hi> expreſs poiſon; and to attend Gods Worſhip miniſtred by the Liturgy, is <hi>to go back into</hi> Egypt, we cannot but ſay, <hi>tell it not in</hi> Gath, <hi>publiſh it not in</hi> Askelon; but if it muſt be heard abroad, let it be known it is a <hi>young Presbyter;</hi> not over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laden with <hi>ſeriouſneſs in conſideration, clearneſs of appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion, or ſtayedneſs of reſolution,</hi> and in this caſe of great concernment <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and in his general nature a <hi>Scotch Remonſtrator;</hi> the men of which name made (by a breach of order in Diſcipline onely) ſuch a Schiſm in the <hi>Scotch Kirkes,</hi> which was not cemented until confuſion brake in upon them.</p>
            <p>Reader, read with freedom what this <hi>Remonſtrator</hi> hath written; onely with it compare <hi>Mr.</hi> Croftons <hi>Plea;</hi> thou wilt ſee his miſtake of the <hi>Queſtion, Mr.</hi> Crofton and his <hi>Argument</hi> is ſo manifeſt, that in all he hath ſaid, he hath ſaid nothing to what he pretendeth to have ſpoken; nor wilt thou need the feſcue of a learned pen, to point thee in the reading thereof.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:100906:4"/>
            <p>I have taken the opportunity of ſaying ſomething by way of reply to his pretended Anſwer; more for the ſake of <hi>truth and thee,</hi> then of the <hi>Author,</hi> (whoſe convicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on I cannot but deſire) that I might ſomething more fully and diſtinctly explain <hi>the caſe in controverſie</hi> now among us; and thoſe principles on which Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> doth deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine it and direct himſelf and others; I have ſo fully known this good man, his principles and practiſe, that I can with confidence, and could not but in duty to Truth ſpeak out the ſame.</p>
            <p>Had Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> been in health, thou mighteſt have had theſe things more acute, exact and polite, but their <hi>plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> may be thine advantage; and it is <hi>verity</hi> not <hi>victory,</hi> is by me purſued; I beg of thee to read without prejudice, and judge without paſſion; I doubt not but thou wilt then give glory to God, and ſee the way in which thou muſt walk; for if thou canſt but once convince thy ſelf that <hi>modification of Gods worſhip is the perſonal act of the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter;</hi> and ſo all <hi>defects and diſorder</hi> therein is his <hi>perſonal ſin;</hi> and that attendance on Gods Worſhip is thy <hi>direct act and poſitive duty;</hi> this or that Miniſterial mode is to thee <hi>an accident</hi> put upon thee by the Miniſter who miniſtreth thereby; and that to ſtumble at this or that becauſe <hi>hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane,</hi> which God hath determined, and the nature of the thing doth direct to be <hi>humane,</hi> is a very great vanity, thou wilt ſee cauſe to diſmiſs thy ſcruples, and to do in <hi>Conſcience,</hi> what carnal policy and ſelf inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt (poor reaſons below a Chriſtian) (<hi>viz.) fear of a Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Law, or deſire to hear a good Sermon</hi> will allow thee in, but can never make lawful to thee.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Farewel.</salute>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="digest_of_quotations">
            <pb facs="tcp:100906:4"/>
            <head>Leaſt the <hi>Remonſtrator</hi> and his over-affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onate Adherents ſhould ſay I have in the enſuing Tract ſtated the Queſtion in coutroverſie otherwiſe then it is ſtated in Mr. <hi>Croftons Reformation not Separation,</hi> (the falſe-hood of which is manifeſt from the whole ſcope of that Book) I have thought it convenient to tranſcribe ſuch ſentences in that Book which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain the <hi>Hinge,</hi> and <hi>Cryſis</hi> of this Ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e of Conſcience, which thou mayſt take as followeth.</head>
            <q>
               <bibl>Title Pag</bibl>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>R.</hi> Croftons <hi>Plea for Communion with the Church, under thoſe corruptions, and by that</hi> diſorderly Miniſtration, <hi>to which he cannot conform, nor by it adminiſter.</hi>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Epiſtle to the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der.</bibl>
               <hi>We muſt either withdraw from the Prayers and</hi> publique worſhip <hi>of God in this Church, or attend it by this</hi> diſguiſed Miniſteral mode and order.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>In the Book. pa. 2</bibl>
               <hi>In the uſe hereof I muſt of neceſſity attend that order of</hi> adminiſtration, <hi>againſt which I have pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liquely witneſſed.</hi>
            </q>
            <q>
               <pb facs="tcp:100906:5"/>
               <bibl>Page. 3.</bibl>
               <hi>My reſolution to attend thoſe</hi> corrupt Adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, <hi>and that</hi> diſorderly Service of God, <hi>until God pleaſe to bring me forth, and make me drink the water of the Sanctuary in purer Veſſels.</hi>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Page. 6.</bibl>
               <hi>At preſent I have no choiſe, if I will attend Gods ſolemn publique worſhip I muſt do it in this place and</hi> Order, <hi>or not at all.</hi>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Page. 16.</bibl>
               <hi>Will any object the prophaneſs of the Miniſters, the rudeneſs and diſorder of</hi> Miniſtration; <hi>we yeild it is too viſible, but more vile</hi> adminiſtrators, <hi>and irregular</hi> adminiſtrations <hi>cannot be, then were the Sons of</hi> Eli <hi>in their ſervice.</hi>
            </q>
            <q>
               <hi>Specifying extrinſecal corruptions, which do not vitiate the Subject; Mr.</hi> Crofton <hi>in our Caeſe menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oneth theſe.</hi>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Pa. 21, 22.</bibl>Rude unſuitabe Miniſterial Method and Order (<hi>which is the Veſſel and onely inſtrument of convey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance</hi>) of Adminiſtration. <hi>Our impoſed</hi> Method, diſorderly Method <hi>of Prayer, under all which Gods</hi> Ordinances <hi>abide a ſubject compleat, truely and formerly Exiſtent, and diſtinct from theſe ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peradded corruptions, operative unto Salvation, and therefore muſt not be declined or diſowned.</hi>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Page 24.</bibl>
               <hi>The</hi> Adminiſtrations <hi>of Gods Worſhip among us, is indeed nauceous, but not void and venemous, our waters are bitter and pudled but not poyſonous, to be plain under all our corruptions, we muſt not, we cannot, we dare not deny the matter and eſſential form of Gods Ordinances, and worſhip is continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to us.</hi>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Pag. 25.</bibl>
               <hi>I confeſs their Common-Prayer is my burden, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of its</hi> defects and diſorder, <hi>and the rudeneſs of the</hi> Miniſterial Method <hi>&amp;c. yet I find in it no matter to which a ſober ſerious Chriſtian may not ſay,</hi> Amen. <hi>and though I diſtaſt the</hi> miniſterial Method, <hi>I cannot diſown the Eſſential form of Prayer.</hi>
            </q>
            <q>
               <pb facs="tcp:100906:5"/>
               <bibl>Pag. 26.</bibl>
               <hi>My good friend, is their no difference between a calling on the onely true God in the name of Chriſt, though in a</hi> defective, rude, confuſed, unfitting order, <hi>and praying unto Saints and dumb Idols be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the</hi> diſorderly Adminiſtration <hi>of the worſhip for matter and form, Gods own appointment, and the Ordinance nullifying adminiſtration in an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known tongue; ſo long as we enjoy in her the matter and eſſential form of Gods Worſhip and Ordinances, though in an</hi> Humane, Unfit, Corrupt, Miniſterial Method, <hi>and</hi> Order, <hi>with ſome vain and needleſs appendents of humane invention, we are not without confidence of Gods preſence, and a poſſibility of ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation; we therefore are without a ſufficient ground for ſeparation or non-communion.</hi>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Pag. 35.</bibl>
               <hi>With all peaceable ſubmiſſion embrace ſuch degrees of Reformation, of the extrinſecal</hi> Order <hi>and</hi> Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterial Method <hi>of Gods Worſhip, enjoying the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance in the eſſential form thereof.</hi>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Pag. 36.</bibl>
               <hi>Shall we not acknowledge Gods mercy in affording us, and humbly uſe the ſubſtance of his own worſhip, celebrated in a</hi> diſorderly way and Method?</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Pag. 37.</bibl>
               <hi>I muſt profeſs to all that fear God, I ſee no ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent cauſe to ſatisfie my conſcience, or to plead before my God, on which to refuſe communion with her, (the Church) and attendance on Gods ſolemn publique Worſhip, under her rude</hi> miniſterial method, <hi>for that duty is not warrantably ſuperſeded by another mans iniquity.</hi>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Pag 40.</bibl>
               <hi>I confeſs the</hi> miniſterial order, <hi>and</hi> method <hi>of publique worſhip, and prayer is purely humane, within the power of the Miniſters thereof, and ſo indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent it ought not to be preſcribed and impoſed.</hi>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Pag. 41.</bibl>
               <hi>This is not my Caſe and Queſtion, but whether ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn, publique worſhip, my poſitive duty, &amp;c. which
<pb facs="tcp:100906:6"/> cannot by reaſon of my confinement be enjoyed, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out my attendance on that</hi> irregular, unſuitable me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod and confuſed order, <hi>may be warrantably ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeded, &amp;c.</hi>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Page 42.</bibl>
               <hi>The</hi> miniſterial method <hi>of Gods Ordinances, is charged on the Miniſters, not on the members of the Churches.</hi>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Page 49.</bibl>
               <hi>I fear to be charged with the omiſſion of Gods pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique worſhip celebrated in Chriſts Church, though with extrinſecal corruption, and in a rude</hi> miniſterial Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <hi>which ought to be reformed.</hi>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Page 69.</bibl>
               <hi>The</hi> miniſterial mode <hi>impoſed, and ſinfully recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved (by ſuch who ſubjugate their Miniſtry) not viti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ating the ſubject, nor nullifying the Ordinances of God, will not warrant my non-attendance on them.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>Christian Reader.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Impartially judge upon theſe paſſages, whether Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> doth not clearly diſtinguiſh be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Gods Worſhip ſubſtantially exiſting in matter and eſſential form, and the humane miniſterial mode by which it is exhibited in and to the Church, and ſo he hath fixed the <hi>Hinge</hi> and <hi>Cryſis</hi> of this controverſie on this Notion; (<hi>viz.) The defect and diſorder of the Miniſterial Mode, is not to the Members of the Church a ſufficient ground for non communion in Gods Worſhip, fully, formally, exiſting by it;</hi> whilſt the <hi>Remonſtrator</hi> hath not diſcerned this, he hath fought with his own Fancy, in his pretended Anſwer to Mr. <hi>Crofton.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="pamphlet">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:100906:6"/>
            <head>Jerubbaall Juſtified: OR, A Plain rebuke to the High (pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) humble Remonſtrance and Plea againſt Mr. <hi>Croftons</hi> Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation not Separation.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Worthy Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>YOurs the 12. inſtant I received, and with it a Book entituled <hi>Jerubbaal,</hi> or the <hi>Pleader impleaded,</hi> which pretendeth to anſwer <hi>Mr. Crofton's Reformation not Separation:</hi> in good time ſir, hath <hi>Mr. Crofton's</hi> pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers paſt nine Months in private from hand to hand, and four Moneths in publique in the world and now anſwered: if it be to purpoſe, and truth be beaten out it is well, <hi>I</hi> will ſay <hi>better late then never.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have not ſir Communicated the Book to <hi>Mr. Crofton</hi> as you do deſire, his late ſickneſs (not yet recovered) h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>th diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>capacitated him for ſuch work: but I have read this <hi>hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Remonſtrance,</hi> and find in it a Spirit <hi>ſufficiently high:</hi> I ſhall adventure to give you, (and if you pleaſe the world) my thoughts concerning this <hi>impleading Plea, againſt Mr. Crof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton's Plea for communion with the Church under thoſe corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and by that diſorderly Miniſtration to which he cannot con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form, nor by it Adminiſter:</hi> And truly Sir, This Book maketh a great cry, but yieldeth little wool, it may ſerve the ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple (whoſe good affections to purity lead their judgement not only from, but againſt duty) to make a noiſe <hi>Mr. Crof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton is anſwered:</hi> but the<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Iudicious Reader will ſoon ſee
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:100906:7"/> there is in it <hi>vox preterea nihill,</hi> and that <hi>Mr. Crofton</hi> is as far from being anſwered, as he was before.</p>
            <p>This Author having paſſed his <hi>Mindus like part</hi> built on his own Judgement of the <hi>expediency</hi> of it: (it is reaſon he enjoy<note place="margin">Page 15.</note> his fancy in his own fabrick) he abruptly aſſaults <hi>Mr. Crofton</hi> on the moſt groſs and manifeſt miſtake of the <hi>man,</hi> the <hi>na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur of his Book,</hi> and the <hi>form</hi> and <hi>force of his Argument,</hi> which could poſſibly befall and miſguide any Antagoniſt whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever.</p>
            <p>Sir, This Gentleman miſtaketh <hi>Mr. Crofton, and the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall nature of his book:</hi> he accounteth (and that with more then ordinary heat and confidence) <hi>Mr. Crofton</hi> the <hi>Mecae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas and Advocate of the Liturgy and Common prayer book, and an accuſer of the bretheren:</hi> he apprehendeth <hi>Mr. Crofton's Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pa. 14. 30.</note> 
               <hi>not ſeparation</hi> to be a <hi>Plea for the Liturgy,</hi> and an <hi>Indictment, or accuſation of the Saints, cujus contrarium verum eſt,</hi> how juſt, ſober, or warrantable thoſe his apprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are, let all impartiall, unprejudiced men judge.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mr. Crofton an Advocate for the</hi> Engliſh <hi>Liturgy,</hi> who can have the face to ſay it? How will that appear? hath he not preached and written againſt it? did he ever retract? doth he conform to it? or conſent to read it? was not his known oppoſition to it apprehended to be the cauſe of his vexati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and bonds he met with in <hi>Staffordſhire</hi> in his late Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vells? can envy it ſelf oppoſe <hi>Mr. Crofton</hi> to <hi>Mr. Crofton:</hi> his enemies being Judges, never was any man more ſquare and ſtable to himſell then is <hi>Mr. Crofton:</hi> theſe things do indeed give cauſe to call him <hi>Jerubbaal</hi> and make it ſuſpicious he is the <hi>Gideon</hi> who threw down the Altar (if the Liturgy muſt be ſo accounted) of <hi>Baall:</hi> on what ground could this pretender, to reaſon and religion, cry <hi>Mr. Crofton</hi> is the <hi>Mecaenas and Advocate for the Liturgy:</hi> hath not <hi>Mr. Crofton's</hi> Conteſts, actings and ſufferings, manifeſted him a Monument of Gods Grace and Truth; and Sectarian rage and falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood: will men needs reproach him with that, which none hath as he reſiſted? Oh Sir, <hi>Mr. Crofton</hi> hath pleaded for <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion in the Liturgy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is falſe ſir, he hath pleaded no ſuch thing, his Plea is for <hi>Communion with Gods Church, in Gods Ordinances and
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:100906:7"/> worſhip, though Adminiſtred by the Liturgy,</hi> and that onely in caſe of <hi>neceſſity,</hi> when we cannot otherwiſe enjoy ſolemn publique worſhip: it is one thing to <hi>commnnicate in the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgie</hi> ſimply and abſtractedly conſidered, this ſuppoſeth an <hi>aſſent unto it,</hi> and a <hi>perſonall acting in and by it</hi> as a Liturgy: for this <hi>Mr. Crofton</hi> hath never yet ſpoken one word: It is another thing to <hi>communicate in, and Religiouſly attend Gods Worſhip Adminiſtred by the Liturgy,</hi> in which the Liturgy is no more but the <hi>vehiculum</hi> inſtrument of conveyance and humane Miniſtration: the formality of <hi>Mr. Crofton's</hi> Plea is this: the <hi>Liturgie is a rude and diſorderly Miniſtration, an evil which ought to be aboliſhed, by which he cannot Adminiſter, but it is not an evil of that nature, to viſiate the Subject, nullify and deſtroy Gods worſhip, and ſo warrant the peoples withdrawing from that becauſe of this.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vulgus non diſtinguit,</hi> that the over zealous vulgar ſhould account this a Plea for <hi>Communion in the Liturgy</hi> is no won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der: whilſt a man of learning doth it with all confidence, is a <hi>withſtanding</hi> of an inſerence which the premiſſes will not allow, a <hi>juſtification</hi> of the premiſſes, as true and good, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not a man plead: men muſt in caſe of need drink water in unclean veſſels, or affirm Citizens muſt not looſe all for want of asking by the rude dialect of their Recorder: but he muſt be concluded the <hi>Mecaenas</hi> of <hi>Barbariſime</hi> and nonſence, and <hi>Advocate</hi> for the <hi>Queen</hi> of <hi>Sluts!</hi> may not <hi>Mr. Crofton</hi> deny ſuch diſorder to be a ſufficient ground for <hi>Seceſſion</hi> from Gods worſhip, but he muſt needs be the defender of that diſorder? According to this ſober Logick is <hi>Mr. Crof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> tauntingly repreſented <hi>the accuſer of the brethren:</hi> and his Book branded as an <hi>Indictment againſt the Saints,</hi> what cauſe is there for this high charge, whom, when, where, and whereof hath <hi>Mr. Crofton</hi> accuſed? This Author calls him <hi>his accuſer,</hi> he ſhall do well to put him to ſhame by tell<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the world whereof <hi>Mr. Crofton</hi> accuſed him, <hi>Mr. Crof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> doth in his book ſuggeſt <hi>groundleſſe, unwarantable, Secoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi>
               <note place="margin">Page 29.</note> 
               <hi>from, voluntary non-communion in Gods worſhip, is a private or negative Separation; the firſt act towards a poſitive and totall Sepeparation,</hi> but is this to <hi>accuſe the bretheren?</hi> cannot a Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter ſuggeſt the ſinful nature of an act, but he muſt be
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:100906:8"/> arraigned as an <hi>Accuſer of the bretheren,</hi> oh Charity! oh So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>briety!</p>
            <p>Sir, Who readeth <hi>Mr. Croftons</hi> book; and ſeeth not that it is ſo far from an <hi>Indictment or Accuſation of others,</hi> that it is a <hi>ſober, ſerious, and neceſſary Apology for himſelf,</hi> and his own practice moſt groundleſly, unchriſtianly and incharitably <hi>accuſed by others;</hi> and thoſe, ſome of the bretheren; who ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver adminiſtred, or attempted to reprove the things whereof they did accuſe him; in his whole Conflicts for Reformation, he had proteſted he <hi>could communicate in Gods worſhip under that order, by which he could not admineſter;</hi> comming to practice his principles, what Calumnies what Cenſures did accuſe him of defection and Apoſtacy? and conſtrain theſe Letters by way of Apology for himſelf, And this, thus extorted by falſe accuſations, is moſt falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly accuſed to be an <hi>accuſation of the brethren;</hi> Oh! Charity! Oh Sobriety!</p>
            <p>Sir, We cannot expect he ſhould rightly take up <hi>Mr. Crofton's Argument,</hi> who hath ſo groſſely miſtaken <hi>himſelf,</hi> and the <hi>generall nature of his work,</hi> let me obſerve to you his miſtake in the very form, and ſo in the force of what he is pleaſed humbly to tearm <hi>Mr. Croftons Doome Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Page 15.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Having paſſed his many needleſs diſtinctions, he profeſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth himſelf a <hi>negative and partiall Sepatiſt;</hi> he is beſt, ſee to his Warrant, leaſt being looſed from the Harbour he be driven he knows not whither, I am glad he diſavoweth <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitive Separation, gathering a ſelect Company into a Corner,</hi> ſome who ſhreudly gueſs who this Author is, think they durſt preſume to charge him as peccant in this reſpect; but ſure I am <hi>Mr. Crofton,</hi> and other good men, are no little grieved to obſerve ſome Presbyters, not only <hi>abſent</hi> from publique aſſemblies, but alſo <hi>celebrate the Lords day</hi> by preaching and Miniſtration of the Lords ſupper, to a ſelect Company <hi>in private,</hi> as if they were deſigned to verefie that Independant Calumny; (<hi>Presbiterated Churches are gathered Churches.</hi>)</p>
            <p>His Separation ſtated, this Antagoniſt aſſaults <hi>Mr. Crofton's</hi> Conſiderations; that he might fence with better ſucceſſe, he forceth the chief of them into this ſyllogiſme according
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:100906:8"/> to his own fancy, not <hi>Mr. Croftons</hi> Argument.</p>
            <p>Communion with the Church, viſible in all acts of ſolemn Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique worſhip; is an eſſential part of the Sanctification of the Sabbath or Lords day, and indiſpenſable Duty of every par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular<note place="margin">Pa. 15. 16.</note> Chriſtian to be onely ſuperſeded by an inevitable ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity &amp;c.</p>
            <p>This is indeed <hi>Mr. Crofton's</hi> propoſition; on which this man doth aſſume, as that which he ſaith, <hi>muſt be</hi> the aſſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and accordingly ſtateth the Concluſion.</p>
            <p>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>But Communion with the Church of England in her Liturgy, or Common-Prayer (called Divine Service) is Communion with the Church viſible in ſolemn publique Worſhip.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>ERGO. Communion with the Church of <hi>England</hi> in her Liturgy or Common-Prayer is an eſſentiall part of the Sanctification of the Sabbath or Lords day, and indiſpenſable duty, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Sir, this Argument thus framed is a monſtrous Argnment; eſpecially to come from <hi>Mr. Crofton;</hi> they that ever heard him preach, read his writings, know his perſon, principles or practice can believe him, ſuch a <hi>Mecaenas and Advocate for the Engliſh Liturgy and Common-Prayer-Book,</hi> as to aſſent and conclude <hi>Communion in it, to be an Eſſential part of the Sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication of the Sabbath;</hi> So as that the Sabbath or Lords day cannot be ſanctified where the Service-book is not attend<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed, aſſented to, and acted in.</p>
            <p>But Sir: What ground or reaſon in <hi>Mr. Crofton's</hi> Plea hath this Antagoniſt, which neceſſitateth this Aſſumption and Concluſion as that which he tells us mnſt be.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mr. Crofton's</hi> Book is an Epiſtle to a Friend, his Argument is not (therefore) logically formed, but very legible in the Connexion and ſcope of his diſcourſe; but this Author doth not in his book, or Margin, cite, or refer his Reader to one ſingle ſentence, or word on which he bottometh this <hi>aſſumption and concluſion</hi> as that which <hi>muſt be,</hi> he indeed hath<note place="margin">Page 22.</note> confidence enough to affirm. <hi>Mr. Crofton</hi> ſaith, the <hi>Liturgy or Common-Prayer is an act of ſolemn publique worſhip:</hi> but doth not tell us where he ſaith it; and I am ſure I have read all that he hath written, and I never found that he ſaid it; I
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:100906:9"/> muſt ſay, Sir, they ſay ſo of this <hi>humble Remonſtrator,</hi> though ſpoken with ſo high conſidence, is not a ſufficient ground for credit: the rather, becauſe the queſtion <hi>Mr. Crofton</hi> did diſcuſſe, and was to bring into concluſion was not; whether <hi>Communion in the Liturgy or Common-Prayer-Book was an eſſential part of the ſanctification of the Sabboth:</hi> Truly ſir, <hi>Mr. Crofton</hi> hath diſputed fairly, if onely this Antago<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſt can find his ſillogyſme conclude, what never came into his queſtion: his logick hath lately failed him very much: Sir, ſure I am? whoſoever ſhall read and regard the ſcope of what <hi>Mr. Crofton</hi> hath written on this Argument ſhall find another <hi>aſſumption and concluſion,</hi> then what the zeal and prejudice of this <hi>Remonſtrator</hi> hath aſſumed and concluded: the true ſtate and form of <hi>Mr. Crofton's</hi> Sillogiſme is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt to be this.</p>
            <p>
               <list>
                  <item>Communion with the Church viſible in Gods ſolemn publique worſhip is an eſſential part of the ſanctification of the Sabbath and indiſpenſable duty.</item>
                  <item>But Communion with the Engliſh Church in the worſhip by her celebrated, is Communion with the Church viſible in Gods ſolemn publique worſhip.</item>
                  <item>ERGO. Communion with the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Church (having no opportunity with any other) in the worſhip of her Celebrated is to me an eſſential part of the ſanctification of the Sabbath, and indiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſable duty.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>This Argument Sir, is far from <hi>aſſuming and concluding the Communion in the Liturgy,</hi> is, <hi>an eſſentiall part of the ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication of the Sabbath, and indiſpenſable duty,</hi> and that the <hi>worſhip celebrated in the Engliſh Church,</hi> muſt be the <hi>Subject</hi> predicated in the <hi>aſſumption</hi> of <hi>Mr. Crofton's</hi> Argument: is manifeſt to every one who obſerveth theſe paſſages in his amplifying the conſideration which containeth this Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</p>
            <p n="1">1 <hi>Communion with the</hi> Engliſh <hi>Church in the worſhip by her celebrated; notwithſtanding the defects and diſorders in Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration thereof;</hi> was the queſtion <hi>Mr. Crofton</hi> did diſpute, and muſt bring into his concluſion.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:100906:9"/>2. He ſaith to his friend, <hi>you yet enjoy a liberty of worſhiping God in due and right order, and may drink the waters of the ſanctuary in clean veſſels</hi> i. e. VVithout the Liturgy its Rites and order (it is manifeſt this he intended) <hi>long may you en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy</hi>
               <note place="margin">Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion not Seperati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</note> 
               <hi>it, and if God take pleaſure in me he will in due time reſtore me to it,</hi> Sr. is it likely Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> would aſſume and conclude <hi>the Liturgy is that ſolemn publick worſhip which is an eſſential</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pag 6.</note> 
               <hi>part of the ſanctification of the Sabbath, and indiſpenſable duty;</hi> whilſt he profeſſeth he had <hi>ſanctified the Sabbath, and worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped God without it,</hi> and hoped for a <hi>reſtored liberty ſo to do again</hi> as a token of divine favour to him; he acknowledgeth it to be his friends priviledge, prayeth the continuance, feareth the loſs of it; that he did <hi>enjoy a liberty to worſhip God in due and right order without the Liturgy,</hi> he complaineth of of it as his <hi>affliction that he had no choice,</hi> but was under a <hi>neceſsity of attending Gods worſhip in this order Miniſtred,</hi> or <hi>he muſt enjoy no ſolemn publick worſhip of God.</hi> Sr. all men muſt confeſs thoſe things will not ſquare with an argument that ſhall conclude <hi>Communion in the Liturgy is an eſſential part of the ſanctification of the Sabbath &amp;c.</hi> but they are exactly ſquare with an Argument for <hi>Communion with the Church in Gods woſhip there celebrated, though Miniſtred with rudneſs and diſorder.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> as a conſcientious Chriſtian, and ſerious Caſuiſt, having concluded <hi>Communion in Gods worſhip was his indiſpenſable duty, in the general;</hi> enquireth what <hi>ſpecialty</hi> might become a <hi>moral bar,</hi> and <hi>warrantable ſuperſedeas</hi> to the<note place="margin">Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion not Separati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> ſame, hereupon he conſidereth what is pleaded by the Separatiſts who abound among us; and among other things the <hi>Liturgie</hi> by which Gods worſhip was miniſtred in and to the Church, admitting the <hi>defects, diſorders, and corruption</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pag. 25.</note> 
               <hi>charged on the ſame,</hi> he concludeth they are <hi>great,</hi> and <hi>evil,</hi> but not an evil of that <hi>nature</hi> and <hi>quality,</hi> as to conſtitute a <hi>ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient bar</hi> to <hi>Communion</hi> in Gods worſhip miniſtred by the ſame. Sr. it is manifeſt the worſhip concluded by Mr. <hi>Crof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tons</hi> argument. (and the ſcope of his whole diſcourſe on this conſideration,) is diſtinct from, though <hi>miniſtred by the Liturgie,</hi> and that this is conſidered as a moral bar, or <hi>war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantable ſuperſedeas</hi> to that, but is found inſufficient.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:100906:10"/>
            <p>Sr. our Antagoniſt having thus miſtaken and misformed Mr. <hi>Croftons</hi> argument, muſt needs be concluded to fight with the fancies of his own prejudice; and ſo <hi>I</hi> might diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſs him, but Sr. I ſeek verity, not victory, and would if poſſible he may ſee his miſtake more plainly upon the whole caſe of this Controvercy, in wich Mr. <hi>Croftons</hi> conflict is the more uncomfortable becauſe ſingle, and failed by thoſe whoſe place and duty oblige them to his ſuccour: but the Conqueſt is moſt certain to him fighting for the truth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all extreams for <hi>vincit veritas:</hi> I would therefore di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect a word to this Remonſtrator, and tell him in his ear, if inſtead of thoſe many needleſs and ſome groundleſs di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctions he hath multiplied, he had well weighed and cloſely purſued the <hi>Criticiſmes</hi> in this caſe ſtated by Mr. <hi>Crof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi> he had ſaved this labour, or written with better ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs, and more ſatisfaction to his Reader, if he will not be offended <hi>I</hi> will note unto him a diſtiction or two, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to which Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> doth move, and on which this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie doth depend.</p>
            <p>Sr. This Remonſtrator maketh much adoe, in diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhing<note place="margin">Pag. 22.</note> ſolemn publick worſhip, by <hi>perſons, place,</hi> and <hi>real<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity,</hi> in which he fighteth with his ſhadow, for Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> would not differ with him, about them; though <hi>I</hi> believe he will diſlike his expreſſions concerning them, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead hereof he ſhould have obſerved Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> hath di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhed between.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>The ſubſtance of ſolemn publick worſhip,</hi> which coſiſteth in the <hi>matter,</hi> and <hi>eſſential form of every ordinance,</hi> both which muſt be determined by the Lord and directed in his word.</item>
               <item>2. <hi>The Miniſterial mode of worſhip,</hi> or that humane dreſs, in and by which its celebrated in and to the Church, which is not determined by the Lord, nor directed o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe then as to its general nature, as that it be <hi>ſerious, reverend, grave,</hi> and the like, in the word, but is wholy left to the wiſdom and faithfulneſs of ſuch to whom the Miniſtration of ſolemn publick worſhip is committed.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Unto this diſtinction our Remonſtrator ſhould have ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded this ſecond <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:100906:10"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>Communion in Gods worſhip, thus or thus adminiſtred,</hi> which conſiſts in an humble, reverend, attendance on, and acting in the worſhip of God, as hearkening to the petitions pronounced, and ſighing or ſpeaking an Amen to them, and the like.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Communion in this or that mode of miniſtration:</hi> ſo as to aſſent unto it, and act decently in it: as the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters adminiſtration by it, or the peoples perſonal actings in popular Reſponds, contamations or cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral geſtures, required by it without any relation to, or direction from the worſhip of God.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Sr. Theſe diſtinctions are manifeſt in themſelves and manifeſtly <hi>neceſſary to all underſtanding Chriſtians</hi> the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God in its <hi>ſubſtance</hi> conſiſting of <hi>matter, and eſſential form,</hi> is clearly diſtinct from the <hi>humane dreſs,</hi> and <hi>miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial mode</hi> by which it is celebrated in and to the Church; preaching the word is <hi>Gods worſhip,</hi> by him determined: for matter, <hi>his word, will and mind,</hi> for form <hi>preached, ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnly ſpoken, diſcourſed</hi> in and to his Church: but that the preaching be an <hi>analytical explication,</hi> or <hi>metaphraſtical ampli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication</hi> of any portion of Scripture, whether it be by <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, Reaſon, and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe,</hi> or onely a diſcourſe <hi>argumentative to confirm an Article of faith, or confute an errour</hi> is ind<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>fferent, undetermined by the Lord, left to the wiſdom and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs of the Preacher; and this or that mode is clearly diſtinct from <hi>Gods Ordinance of preaching,</hi> which is fully, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mally exiſtent in and to the Church by any, by every mode which the edification of the Church ſhall dictate, and the ability, wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and faithfulneſs of the Preacher ſhall determine.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Methods and Phraſes</hi> of adminiſtration of the <hi>Sacraments</hi> by previous or ſubſequent <hi>exhortation to duty, diſcourſes of their nature, uſe, and end;</hi> and prayers ſo modified and phraſed, are apparently diſtict from the <hi>Sacraments,</hi> thoſe parts of Gods worſhip, which ſubſtantially exiſt, when water, bread and wine, the <hi>right matter,</hi> are miniſterially applied in the name of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Son and Holy Ghoſt, as ſignificant ſealing memorials of Chriſts death, body and blood; <hi>the aſſential form of Gods ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance and inſtituted worſhip.</hi> The ſame Sr. is conſiderable in prayer, the ſubſtance of which ordinance doth conſiſt in a <hi>calling upon God in the name of Chriſt for things agreeable to his will,</hi> ſo
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:100906:11"/> that where things agreeable to his will is the <hi>matter;</hi> and calling upon God in the name of Chriſt is the <hi>form;</hi> by whatſoever <hi>hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane mode, order of ſpeech, phraſe, words, ſentences,</hi> the ſame is performed in, and for the Church it doth ſubſtantially exiſt, is diſtinct and to be abſtracted from the ſame.</p>
            <p>Sr. on this firſt, the ſecond diſtiniction doth manifeſtly ariſe, <hi>viz. it is one thing to Communicate in Gods worſhip,</hi> preaching pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, or Sacraments, ſubſtantially exiſting in any, in every miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial mode, and dreſs by which it doth exiſt in and to the Church; although theſe cannot be divided when Gods worſhip doth ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſt in to the Church (for God cannot be worſhipped by men, without the humane miniſtration of his ordinances in ſome<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table mode) yet they may be eaſily and plainly diſtinguiſhed ſo as that the Church and particular members may know their di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct intereſt in Communion; the people in the general nature of the worſhip, ſubſtantially exiſting <hi>Gods,</hi> in matter and form, in and by any humane mode whatſoever, as that which concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth and ſo charged on them, all in common, and the Miniſter the ſpecifical and miniſterial mode of adminiſtration of Gods wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip between God and his people; which is perſonally incum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bent, and charged on him by vertue of that office for modifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of Gods ordinances, which he hath received from the Lord.</p>
            <p>Sr. Theſe diſtinctions are not more manifeſt in themſelves, then that they are <hi>Mr. Croftons, in this very caſe and controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie; I</hi> would not that this Remonſtrator ſhould think I come to relieve Mr. <hi>Crofton,</hi> with any diſtinctions, which are not <hi>his,</hi> and plainly <hi>legible</hi> in the <hi>plea</hi> he doth implead, be pleaſed therefore to obſerve <hi>Mr. Croftons</hi> own words. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder all our corruptions, we muſt not, we cannot, we dare not deny the matter, and eſſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al form of Gods ordinances and worſhip is continued to us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Again <hi>Sr.</hi> in this very and ſpecial caſe of the <hi>Litugy</hi> Mr. <hi>Crof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi>
               <note place="margin">Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion not Separati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> thus writeth; <hi>I confeſs the Common-prayer is my burden, by reaſon of its defects and diſorder, and the rudeneſs of the Miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial method; I ſtand convinced it ought to be altered, yee aboliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Yet</hi> I <hi>must confeſs I finde no matter in it, to which on a charitable interpretation, a ſober ſerious Chriſtian may not ſay or can denie his Amen: and though I diſtast the Miniſterial method,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Page 25.</note> 
               <hi>I cannot but obſerve in it the eſſential form of prayer</hi> viz. <hi>a calling <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> the name <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:100906:11"/>
            <p>Sr. Can any tearms make theſe diſtinctions more plain, and yet Sr. theſe occaſion in Mr. <hi>Croftons</hi> plea for his Communion two more, which do ariſe from, and depend on theſe.</p>
            <p>The firſt concerning corruptions, which he conſidereth to<note place="margin">Pa. 20. 21 22, 23.</note> be <hi>intrinſecal vitiating the ſubject,</hi> nullifying Gods ordinance, deſtroying Gods worſhip, and ſo neceſſitating ſeperation.</p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>Extrinſecal ſuperadded to, concomitant with, and converſant about</hi> Gods Ordinances, which notwithſtanding doth exiſt for matter and eſſential form perfect and entire, capable of due opperation, as <hi>ſtinking fiſh doth nouriſh,</hi> or <hi>water pudled, or taken in an unclean veſſel</hi> doth quench the thirſt, and preſerve life.</item>
            </list>
            <p>This diſtinction, this humble Remonſtrator, doth with ſome ſcorn obſerve, and paſs by as of little or no weight, though the caſe of conſcience now controverted, doth depend upon it, and directeth the next diſtinction <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>Reformation</hi> which ſuppoſeth the ſubject to continue <hi>ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tially the ſame,</hi> but attended with ſome <hi>circumſtantial cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions,</hi> the removal of which muſt be endeavoured, but theſe notwithſtanding the ſubject may with ſafety, and it muſt in duty be uſed.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Separation</hi> ſuppoſing the ſubject ſo <hi>viciated,</hi> that it cannot be uſed with ſafety, without ſin, and muſt therefore be ſhun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Theſe diſtinctions moſt humbly ſlighted, I wonder at, that this <hi>Remonſtrator</hi> ſhould flie out ſo high, as to cry out <hi>Mr.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Page 24.</note> 
               <hi>Croftons inſtances of ſtinking fiſh, pudled water and unclean veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels yield not the leaſt ſatisfaction to me;</hi> for it is evident to any impartial Reader his prejudice never ſuffered him, to finde the <hi>form,</hi> and therefore he could not feel the force of the argument; for if the <hi>Liturgie</hi> be but a veſſel though unclean, this argument <hi>extrinſecal corruptions, being conſiſtent with Gods true worſhip, will not warrant a ſeceſſion, or negative ſeparation,</hi> appeareth very cogent, and is well amplified by the inſtance of <hi>pudled wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter or an unclean veſſel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sr.</hi> Theſe diſtinctions being not more manifeſt in themſelves, and to be uſed by Mr. <hi>Crofton,</hi> in the plea which this Antago<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſt doth implead; then to be <hi>Criſis</hi> of this Controverſie; the the hinge on which this great caſe of conſcience doth turn. I will
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:100906:12"/> preſume on my friend ſo far, as to preſent you with ſome ſhort and plain <hi>Aphoriſms</hi> concerning Gods worſhip, and his peoples communion; you may (if you pleaſe) call them Mr. <hi>Croftons Creed concerning communion with Gods Church,</hi> I cannot but commend them to the obſervation of Gods people &amp; conſideration of Gods Miniſters, as thoſe which few ſober men will deny to be true, and being well underſtood would readily direct a godly mans courſe in the hour of temptation which is come upon us.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The <hi>Church Catholick viſible diſtributed</hi> (through ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsity, and good order) to particular Aſſemblies muſt ſanctifie the Lords day by an holy Convocation.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The <hi>Congregation of perticular Chriſtians convened in full and open joynt Aſſembles, to celebrate Gods ſolemn worſhip, is the formality of an holy Convocation:</hi> in which every particular Chriſtian muſt make conſcience to be preſent, and continue from the beginning to the end of the miniſtration of Gods worſhip, they muſt aſſemble on the ſound of the ſilver trumpets, and not depart without the Prieſts bleſsing.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>The worſhip celebrated in the holy Convocation for the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and eſſential form by which it ſubſtantially exiſteth, muſt he determined by the Lord, and by him alone:</hi> all other matter though in a <hi>form</hi> by God directed; or the <hi>matter</hi> without the <hi>form</hi> by him appointed, is <hi>ſupperſtition</hi> to be avoided; a <hi>dogs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head</hi> or <hi>Swines blood</hi> offered by a lawful Prieſt, and with <hi>Levi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical Rights,</hi> and Incenſe in the hands of <hi>Chora Dathan,</hi> and <hi>Abiram,</hi> or a Lamb and Bullock offered by the laweſt of the people at <hi>Dan</hi> and <hi>Bethel,</hi> are eqully abominable to the Lord, Baptiſme by fire in the name of Father Son and holy Ghoſt or by water in the name of God the Father, and time the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of all things is equally void and vile, no worſhip of God.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>All worſhip of mens invention ſuperadded to Gods apoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment muſt be avoided, abandoned by every of Gods people, but Gods worſhip ſubſtantially exiſting with the ſame muſt not be diſowned or declined:</hi> the mountains of Iſrael, the Temple muſt be frequented, devoutly reſorted unto, though the high places be on the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:100906:12"/> one, and the Image of jealouſy be in the other; theſe <hi>ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>added evils</hi> provoke God, but the <hi>Simbolls of his preſence</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued, bind his people to due and conſtant attendance: the <hi>Croſſe in Baptiſme</hi> is to be (if poſſible) avoided but <hi>Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme</hi> formally exiſting muſt not be diſowned, declined, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the other is ſuperadded.</p>
            <p n="5">5 <hi>Gods worſhip celebrated by and among men, muſt be mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred, and exiſt in an and by an humane mode and dreſſe ſuitable to, and ſo fit to edefie ſuch a Creature and ſociety.</hi> Gods word and Sacraments, his peoples prayers, muſt be miniſtred in, and by modes, methods, words and actions, invented by the minde, expreſſed by the tongue, and performed by the hands of men.</p>
            <p n="6">6. <hi>The humane mode and dreſſe, words and phraſes, by which Gods worſhip muſt exiſt, and be miniſtred in and to the Church is not determined by the Lord, but wholly left to the wiſdom and faithfulneſſe of them who miniſter the ſame, hence it comes to paſs,</hi> that the ſubſtance of Gods worſhip continueth the ſame, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of matter and eſſential form by and under various mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterial humane modes; Gods word is preached, though ſome times one way, and ſometimes another; the Sacraments are for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mally adminiſtred, prayers are truly made, and the one and the other is Gods Ordinance, the ſame unto all ſubjected to it, though the miniſtration thereof doth varie according to the various Gifts of the adminiſtrator.</p>
            <p n="7">7. <hi>The humane Miniſterial modification of Gods Ordinances in and to the Church is the formall act of the Miniſteriall Office to be fulfilled, and performed by the Miniſterial guifts, the perſonall abilities, of every individuall Miniſter, who is guifted of God, and ordained by the Church for that purpoſe.</hi> Goſpel Miniſtry is an office in Gods Church authorizing enabling, its ſubjects not to inſtitute any new worſhip for matter or forme, but to Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter the worſhip appointed by the Lord in an humane mode, and order, ſuch as may edefie the Church: the matter is the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termination of God, the Miniſteriall mode is the digeſtion of the man, inveſted with an office to that purpoſe the word and the preaching of it is appointed by God, the mode, and tearms in which it is preached, to reproof inſtruction, or correction is the work of the officer, ordained to preach; he is guifted, and autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rized to dicotomize, divide the word aright; the caſe is the ſame<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:100906:13"/> in Sacraments, Prayer, Cenſures, all which muſt exiſt in, and too the Church by the Miniſterial mode and order, words, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions, in which the Miniſter entruſted with them, doth exhibit the ſame to them: herein each Miniſter muſt employ his Ciniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial guifts, his perſonal abilities; this is the ſervice he muſt do to God, and his Church; he is a ſteward of the Miſteries of God, to diſtribute his maſters Goods with the utmoſt of his <hi>skill</hi> and <hi>faithfulneſſe: dicotomization</hi> of Gods word, <hi>modification of Gods worſhip,</hi> is the work in, and by which he muſt approve himſelf <hi>a werkman which needeth not to be aſhamed:</hi> in this he cannot without ſloath and porfidie aſſume, another mans mode, or ſuffer himſelf to be impoſed upon; ſo as to vail his own received guifts and to adminiſter by the modes, and formes digeſted and compoſed by others.</p>
            <p n="8">8. <hi>The miniſterial mode, and order of Gods worſhip being wholy humane, determined by mens Wiſdom and faithfulneſſe, it is and cannot but be ſubject to much &amp; great corruption in defect, &amp; diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der rudeneſſe, &amp; irreverence in expreſſions;</hi> ſome Miniſters are <hi>raſh and inconſiderate,</hi> unaffected with the <hi>Majeſty of God</hi> to whom they approach, in whoſe ſtead they ſtand, in and to his Church unacquainted with the <hi>nature of the ordinance to be adminiſtred by him: and the quality of the Church in</hi> and to which he doth miniſter (which things are the only dictators of that mode by which they miniſter) there are many times rude, prepoſterous, raſh, irreverent full it may be of non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, and cautologies, in the modes by which he doth miniſter; ſome are <hi>proud and curious,</hi> and in their carnal policy compell an <hi>vniformity,</hi> in miniſterial mode, not ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, yea ſinfull; (reſtraining miniſteriall guifts, and the Churches profit by their variety) theſe pretend to correct ſome mens. rudeneſſe, and irreverence, by impoſing their own preſcribed compoſed formes and modes of miniſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on (to the open violence, and almoſt ſubvertion of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ffice of the Miniſtry) theſe again met, with men of ſloath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, or ſlaviſh ſpirits, who are idle and neglect their own miniſterial guifts; whilſt others (on pretence to peace and obedience to ſuperiors) do admit them the formes com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed by others; betraying the office they have received
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:100906:13"/> from the Lord, no wonder to find defects and diſorders in the miniſterial mode of Gods worſhip, whilſt the ſame is wholly dependent on men of weakneſſe, ſubject to folly and infidelity: the beſt of men and Miniſters need a Prieſt to make attonen ent for their holy things.</p>
            <p n="9">6. <hi>The guilt of all defect and diſorder in the humane miniſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al mode of Gods worſhip is immediately, properly, and directly perſonal, charged on the Miniſter, and on him alone: not on the Church, or any the members thereof.</hi> The guilt is proportio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to the duty, modification is a perſonal duty, charged on the officer appointed to that office: this guilt may indeed (as other ſins) by accident be derived to the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours of the Church, who ſhould, but do not ſet up, and ordain men to the Miniſtry, and ſuſpend, and put down ſuch who want ability, well and rightly to modifie and miniſter Gods worſhip and Ordinances: and to the peo, ple and individual members, when they obſerving de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects and diſorders in the Miniſterial mode of worſhip, do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not grieve for the ſin of others, and complain of it as bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denſom to themſelves; and in liberty of choice, if they do not chooſe better, but ſit contentedly under the ſame. <hi>Eli</hi> by the firſt, brought on himſelfe the ſin of his ſons, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane miniſtration, and the God-fearing <hi>Iſraelites</hi> delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red themſelves by the laſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but there is no common rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon which can derive the ſin of rude Miniſtration on the people.</p>
            <p n="10">10. <hi>All defects, diſorders, rude and impertinent expreſſions, in the hnmane, miniſterial mode of Gods worſhip: are corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, circumſtantiall, and extrinſeal in, and by which Gods wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip may ſubſtantially exiſt in matter, and eſſential form, capable of operation to its appointed end.</hi> The Scriptures are read, though in parts and parcels, and in a corrupt, imperfect tranſlation: all which are evil: and abate the efficacy to edification: but are not ſuch evil, on which we may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude the Seriptures are not read, or cannot edifie the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers: the word is preached, and may profit the hearer, though the Sermon be raw, rude, indigeſted, immethodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal, and in wild and unfit expreſſions. Prayer is preſented to God, though defective in ſome matter, to be deſired,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:100906:14"/> diſorderly in the manner of expreſſions, uttered with ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions, abreviations, pauſes, and poſtings one again: None of theſe evils do vitiate the ſubject, or alter the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter or eſſential form of Gods Ordinance, ſo as to deſtroy the ſubſtance: theſe make Gods worſhip not ſo ſerious, grave, and reverend as it ſhould be: but theſe, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding it doth truly, fully, formally exiſt Gods worſhip: the third, not ſecond Commandement is hereby broken. God's name is truly but not rightly uſed: he is truly worſhipped, but th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe adjunct qualities which ſhould attend his wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip are wanting: the want of reverence and right order in the miniſtration of his Ordinance doth provoke<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> God, but will not conclude he is not at all worſhipped.</p>
            <p n="11">11. <hi>Defects diſorders and corruptions in the miniſterial mode of Gods Ordinances fixed, continued and reiterated, are more ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and offenſive to God, and his people then thoſe which are pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent and tranſient, but both theſe are ſins of one and the ſame nature and quality, and of equal influence on Gods worſhip mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred by the ſame.</hi> Corruptions fixed and reiterated, are more wicked becauſe more deliberately, and wilfully uſed: more offenſive to Gods people becauſe <hi>foreknown:</hi> like the rude miniſtrations of <hi>Elies</hi> ſons, they make the <hi>Lords peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple loath the offerings of the Lord,</hi> but yet they enter not into <hi>Gods Ordinance,</hi> ſo as to <hi>vitiate</hi> the ſame, and make it <hi>ceaſe</hi> to be his prayer, is no leſſe prayer when pronounced by the defective, diſordered forms which are fixed and reite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated; then when expreſſed by the <hi>raw, rude, irreverent modes, preſently conceived</hi> by the Miniſter: the laſt may be more excuſable in the Miniſter, and more comfortable to the people: but <hi>prayer</hi> is as truly formally, exiſtent <hi>Gods worſhip</hi> under the firſt: the <hi>fixed reiteration</hi> of a defective, diſordered miniſterial mode of worſhip <hi>addeth to the degree:</hi> but <hi>altereth not the nature</hi> and <hi>quality</hi> of the ſinne.</p>
            <p n="12">12. No defects, or diſorders in the humane miniſteriall mode, (whether fixed and reiterated in, and by impoſed, and preſcribed forms, or expreſſed in, and by preſent, tranſient conceived forms, in and by which Gods worſhip
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:100906:14"/> doth ſubſtantially exiſt, for matter and form his, in and to his Church) <hi>will warrant any Chriſtians ſeceſſion, volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary withdrawing from the holy Convocation, or non-commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion in Gods worſhip ſo miniſtred:</hi> for theſe, notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Gods worſhip doth <hi>truly, fully, formally</hi> exiſt, capable of operation to its appointed end: 2. This ſin is <hi>purely perſonal,</hi> chargeable on the Miniſter, who ſtandeth charged with the office of miniſterial modification of Gods worſhip, in, and to the Church: the people or particular mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the Church, may and muſt paſſe on this (as other perſonal acts) a <hi>judgement of charity,</hi> which doth direct them to <hi>grieve</hi> for the ſin exiſtent; to <hi>complain of it,</hi> and as they have opportunity to <hi>admoniſh</hi> the ſinner: (though the ſons of <hi>Eli</hi>) of it, <hi>and ſeek the correction and removal</hi> of the ſame; but they have not of it any <hi>judicium publicum,</hi> judgement of <hi>Office,</hi> charged on them, by the ſpecialty of duty: and armed with a <hi>juſt morall power of correction,</hi> ſo as that the ſame ſhould be the neglect of this publique duty become their ſin, and leave its guilt on their ſouls: that Gods worſhip formally exiſt in every mode of miniſtration: every Chriſtian and member of the Church muſt <hi>judge and ſee:</hi> for by this corruption, the holy Convocation ceaſeth, and they worſhip not God: but the <hi>mode it ſelfe</hi> is <hi>perſonally charged</hi> on the Miniſter: the <hi>defect and diſorder</hi> is an accident reſulting from the ſloth, negligence, ignorance, weakneſſe and unfaithfulneſſe of the Miniſter, and an adjunct ſeparable from Gods wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip exiſtent by the ſame.</p>
            <p>Sir<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>I</hi> pray you take good notice of this, that the <hi>pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Chriſtian, and particular members of the Church have no publike judgement of office, concerning the Miniſterial mode of Gods worſhip:</hi> for Sir, it is a notion of much weight, and uſe in this Caſe, and it appeareth plainly true, if the modifying of Gods worſhip, be, as it cannot be denyed to be the <hi>perſonal act of an Officer appointed to that end:</hi> moreover Sir, if the people have a <hi>publique judgement</hi> of the miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial mode of Gods worſhip, we are under a neceſſity of ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving what we ſo much complain againſt, and caſt off, (<hi>viz<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi>)
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:100906:15"/> a <hi>fixed Liturgy</hi> for the mode of Prayer, Preaching, Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of Sacraments: muſt then be kown to the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and judged by them free from all defect and diſorder, before the people can attend Gods worſhip in that Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration: it muſt be confeſſed impoſſible, for a ſingle Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter conſtantly to communicate to every particular mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of his Congregation: the <hi>mode</hi> into which he hath (by his perſonal abilities and miniſterial Gifts) caſt the <hi>word Prayer</hi> and <hi>Sacraments:</hi> no ſerious, ſober Chriſtian can think the people to be guilty of thoſe rude <hi>methods,</hi> indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſted, raw, <hi>expreſſions tautologies, ſoleciſmes,</hi> and <hi>diſorders,</hi> which a Miniſter may utter in his preaching, and praying, yet this is inevitable if the people have a publike judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment by ſpecial office, of the miniſterial mode of Gods worſhip: it is indeed true, the defective, diſordered mode of worſhip which is <hi>fixed, ſtated,</hi> and ſo from time <hi>reiterated</hi> is more obvious and offenſive, then what is tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſient, and ſo by the judgement of charity more burdenſom to the people, the grief of it being continued and renew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: but it is the judgement of office, armed with power to correct, deriveth the guilt of the one, or of the other.</p>
            <p>I hope Sir, our <hi>Remonſtrator</hi> will by this time ſee, that he hath moſt groſſely miſtaken Mr. <hi>Crofton,</hi> and the whole <hi>ſcope and nature of his Plea,</hi> and the very <hi>Criſſis</hi> of our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Controverſie, he will ſure now ſee Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> plead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not for Communion in the Liturgy, he is poſitive in it: <hi>a Miniſter cannot without ſin miniſter Gods worſhip by this</hi> (or a much better) <hi>mode (if generally and excluſively impoſed) of worſhip,</hi> he never yet adviſed, juſtifyed, or defended the peoples perſonal acting, <hi>by conclamations, po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pular reſponds,</hi> and <hi>groundleſſe variation of Geſtures,</hi> the part allotted to the people in, and by it; and this is Sir, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly <hi>Communion in the Liturgit.</hi> Sir, Mr. <hi>Crafton<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> doth conſider the Liturgy in its general nature, a <hi>Miniſterial mode,</hi> conveighing ſome part of Gods ſhorſhip, in, and to the Church, the which he confeſſeth is <hi>defective and diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly,</hi> and therefore the grief and burden of the Lords
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:100906:15"/> people; but it doth not <hi>vitiate, destroy,</hi> or <hi>nullifie</hi> the <hi>worſhip</hi> miniſtred by the ſame; but that it ſubſtantially exiſteth for <hi>matter</hi> and <hi>form</hi> Gods worſhip, capable of operation to its end, by reaſon whereof the people having no choice of a better, and <hi>more orderly miniſterial m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>de,</hi> muſt, (though with grief, and a burdened ſpirit) attend the ſame; blſſing God they have his <hi>ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances,</hi> though in a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> unclean, unhandſome veſſel, or rudely mang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, or <hi>ill favouredly carved;</hi> ſo that <hi>Communion in Gods wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip</hi> thus miniſtred; not <hi>Communion in this miniſterial mode</hi> is Mr. <hi>Croftons</hi> Queſtion.</p>
            <p>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. I havering corrected this <hi>Remonſtrators</hi> moſt groſs miſtakes, ſhall now take a veiw of the ſtrength of his argumentation, in<note place="margin">Pag. 16. 17.</note> what he ſuppoſeth to be an anſwer to <hi>Mr. Crofton's</hi> plea.</p>
            <p>To his falſly formed argument, or Syllogiſme he ſaith, his anſwer ſhall be by</p>
            <list>
               <item>Conceſsion.</item>
               <item>Diſtinction.</item>
               <item>Retortion.</item>
            </list>
            <p>In the firſt part of his anſwer, <hi>viz.</hi> his <hi>Conceſsion</hi> he yieldeth to Mr. <hi>Crofton;</hi> the <hi>truth of the Church of England;</hi> about this we diſpute no longer, onely ſome who will clap him on the back, for appearing an Antagoniſt againſt <hi>Mr. Crofton</hi> will think by<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> this Conceſſion he hath given away his cauſe.</p>
            <p>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. One thing I cannot paſs without obſervation; and that<note place="margin">Pag. 19.</note> is, an expreſſion wildly let fall, to which I cannot conſent to him <hi>viz. perſonal corruptions in ſcandalous profeſſors, or other Church members, (Miniſter (as well as others) the Hophni, and Phineas of our age) defils the Church:</hi> this I underſtand not, nor doth he tell us whether it defile the Church immediately, and of it ſelf, or conſequently and by accident,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:100906:16"/> the defect of the Church, in ſome duty incumbent upon her, intervening<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to derive the ſin unleſs by this laſt way; <hi>perſonal ſin,</hi> and <hi>Church guilt,</hi> are a contradiction: the prophaneſſe of <hi>Elies ſons</hi> was indeed charged on their Father <hi>Eli,</hi> and that by accident onely: but I never read, nor can finde it was charged on the <hi>Church of Iſrael;</hi> the God fearing Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elites did deliver themſelves, by their <hi>robukes of their diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</hi> without forbearing to bring their offerings to the Lord, though they were rudely Miniſtered by prophane hands.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By way of Diſtinction.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here he diſtinguiſheth between Communion by<note place="margin">Pag. 19. 20.</note> 
               <hi>Profeſsion, Participation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How warrantable, and well grounded this diſtinction is, I ſhall not now conſider; I do not finde Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned in it; onely I muſt tell this <hi>Remonſttator,</hi> I underſtand not the neceſſity, and prrviledges he appropriateth to Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion by profeſſion, (if that profeſſion be abſtracted, from, and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to participation) calling upon God, worſhipping, God, and the <hi>viſio ſalvit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ca</hi> are not had<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> or done by a ba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the true religion, but do require perſonal participation, pation, to make man enjoy, the priveledges to them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing.</p>
            <p>Again I muſt tell this Remonſtrator, Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> will denie<note place="margin">Pag. 21.</note> there are many, or indeed any members of the univerſal Church; (he ſure means viſible and militant, or it ſquareth not with his diſcourſe) <hi>who never had opportunity of aſſonating themſelves with, or joynt communion in the ſolemn worſhip of God;</hi> for if they be actual, formal members of the Church viſible, they had an opportunity to be made ſuch; men as we are not mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the Church; ſaving faith may give relation to the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:100906:16"/> Church Catholick inviſible, but memberſhip with the Church Catholick viſible, could not be had without an opportunity of joynt Communion in Gods worſhip in ſome particular Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly.</p>
            <p>The Whole improvement of this diſtinction by this Anta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goniſt is onely to infer what Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> had yielded, yea <hi>inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minis</hi> ſtated, <hi>viz. Communion in Gods worſhip, with Gods Church is an indiſpenſable duty of every ſoul called by the name of God; to be onely ſuperſeded by the real inevitable neceſsity of ſome natural</hi> (ſuch as is humane violence) or moral (ſuch as is the certainty of ſin by ſuch Communion) ba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e. About this therefore we are agreed.</p>
            <p>The Remonſtrator maketh another diſtinction of publick ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn worſhip in reſpect of</p>
            <list>
               <item>Perſons worſhiping.</item>
               <item>Place of worſhip.</item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <hi>Reality of matter, and Conſtitution of the worſhip.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>On what ground he multiplieth theſe diſtinctions I ſee not, unleſs on a meer fancie that Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> determined the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God to be ſolemn publick in, and becauſe of thoſe pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces appointed, and uſed to that end in this nation; unto this<note place="margin">Pag. 26.</note> conjecture I am lead by his hot aſſertion, <hi>locallity under the Goſpel is meer matter of indifferency; God having only ſtamped ſanctity on places among the Jews. Mr. Crofton bearing me wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs:</hi> for which in his Margin he quoteth <hi>Mr. Crofton his Altar worſhip.</hi> page 77. but good Sir, what needs this heat? <hi>Mr. Crofton</hi> did witneſs this aſſertion in his <hi>Altar worſhip:</hi> hath he unſaid it in his <hi>Reformation not Separation?</hi> he pleadeth for communion with the Church: but did he ever confine the Church to any place? he ſaith private perticular members may not withdraw themſelves, or deny communion, with the holy <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation or Church aſſembly,</hi> whereſoever it is held; but he ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:100906:17"/> denyed the <hi>Church or holy corrvocation was convened,</hi> and (if neceſſitated) may be again <hi>convened</hi> in <hi>woods, caves, dens, or poor cottages. Mr. Crofton</hi> doth grant the Church is an <hi>holy convocation</hi> in <hi>any place</hi> aſſembled, but he doth deny that 10. 20, 30, or 40. <hi>private particular Members,</hi> (among whom may be a Miniſter by his office a Publique officer) aſſembled in a <hi>place diſtinct from:</hi> it may be <hi>oppoſite to the Publique Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly,</hi> is a <hi>Church or holy Convocation:</hi> and truly ſhould he grant this, he muſt be at a loſſe how to know a <hi>Conventicle</hi> or determine a <hi>Schiſmatical Aſſembly,</hi> and throw down the Bankes of all Church order.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That the Church of</hi> Englands <hi>Liturgie, or Common-Prayer</hi>
               <note place="margin">P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 28. 29.</note> 
               <hi>(the great Apple of ſtrife) is a part of this Real ſolemn worſhip of God, and Communion with her therein is an indiſpenſable duty I muſt</hi> (ſaith this Antagoniſt) <hi>take leave to deny:</hi> and <hi>Mr. Crofton</hi> will reply to him, <hi>do ſo and welcome;</hi> for greater zealots for the Liturgy, then ever <hi>Mr. Crofton</hi> is like to make, will not once affirm that <hi>the Liturgie is a part of reall ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn worſhip of God:</hi> it is not properly any <hi>worſhip at all;</hi> it cannot then be <hi>reall ſolemn worſhip of God:</hi> the Liturgy in the ſtrict forme, and generall nature of it is <hi>not worſhip</hi> but a <hi>Politicall</hi> (though Eccleſi ſtique) <hi>order and direction,</hi> unto praying, reading the Scriptures, and Miniſtration of Sacraments; methinks this learned man ſhould not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found; <hi>reall ſolemn worſhip,</hi> and a <hi>Political order</hi> relating to ſolemn worſhip; they are in themſelves manifeſtedly di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct. wherein the <hi>Liturgie</hi> doth preſcribe, and impoſe ſet <hi>formes;</hi> and <hi>certain</hi> words by, and in which Prayer, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther parts of worſhip muſt exiſt in, and to the Church it is only a <hi>Miniſterial mode,</hi> exhibiting worſhip; it is not <hi>wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip it ſelf: I</hi> hope this acute diſputant, will not affirm the <hi>form or mode</hi> into which he caſteth, and by which he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſeth <hi>Prayer,</hi> is real ſolemn worſhip: I hope <hi>calling upon God in the name of Chriſt, for things according to his will,</hi> is the <hi>formality of ſolemn worſhip,</hi> and that his, or other mens <hi>formes</hi> expreſſing the ſame, is only the <hi>miniſterial mode,</hi> by which it is exhibited in, and to the Church.</p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:100906:17"/>
            <p>Sr, How vain, and frivolous, are theſe high-flown Epe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thites, which this humble, Remonſtrator doth give the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgy <hi>humane ordinance, ſuper-erogatorie worſhip, arbitrary ſervice, Scripturebitten worſhip:</hi> whilſt it is not at all <hi>worſhip:</hi> but almoſt <hi>a Politick Order; and Miniſterial mode of Worſhip:</hi> but <hi>I</hi> muſt take up: leaſt by <hi>correcting a miſtake,</hi> I alſo be branded to be the <hi>Mecaenas and Advocate of the Liturgy:</hi> We ſhall hear more of this in the next part of his anſwer, which he ſaith is by way of</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Retortion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And what is it that he recorted on <hi>Mr. Crofton?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Communion with the Church of</hi> England, <hi>may be ſuperſeded by reall inevetable neceſſity, exeonceſſis: by Mr. Crofton's own Doctrine, and aſſertion; but mine (that I may put in for a ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſedeas,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Page 31.</note> 
               <hi>is a reall inevetable neceſſity</hi> ſaith the Remonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor: If ſo ſir, is this a <hi>Retortion?</hi> I ſhould have thought it to have been more properly accounted <hi>ajoyning Iſſues, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Mr. Crofton's Rule:</hi> which he could not, doth not, deny to be a <hi>Rule of truth,</hi> not to be avoided: but binding all non-communicants in Gods worſhip to aſſigne and plead the <hi>inevetable neceſſity</hi> which muſt be their warrant for <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coſſion,</hi> ſo as to acquit them from <hi>Schiſme,</hi> or ſinfull ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: Let us hear ſir his <hi>inevetable neceſſity</hi> pleaded, and here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he tells us.</p>
            <list>
               <head>He cannot communicate in two things:</head>
               <item>1. In the Liturgie</item>
               <item>2. In the Sacrament of the Lords Supper.</item>
            </list>
            <p>He cannot <hi>communicate in the Liturgy,</hi> nor did <hi>Mr. Crofton</hi> ever adviſe he ſhould: But I hope he will aſſigne a good reaſon why he cannot <hi>communicate in Gods worſhip Miniſtred by the Liturgy:</hi> he ſaith he joyneth with the Church in<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:100906:18"/> 
               <hi>Prayer, praiſes, and hearing the word:</hi> he ſure will not deny the <hi>reading of the word to be a Publique Ordinance of God, and part of publique ſolemn worſhip:</hi> he will I hope ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt an inevitable neceſſity for his own non-communion in that: and for his <hi>abſence from any, thoſe Prayers which are</hi> by the Church put up unto God.</p>
            <p>The neceſſity of my noncommunion in the Liturgy (ſaith this Remonſtrator) <hi>is grounded on invincible doubts, about the Lawfulneſs of ſuch a conſtitution:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sir, I cannot but pitty the man, <hi>doubts are a Rack to the</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pa. 32.</note> 
               <hi>minde:</hi> and being <hi>invincible</hi> he is like to live in conſtant bondage: Sure I am, <hi>Mr. Crofton</hi> will conſent, he follows his <hi>conſcience</hi> though <hi>erroneous</hi> being duly carefull, and humbly ſtudious to <hi>certifie, rightly inform</hi> the ſame: But ſir, methinks he vexeth his ſoul, entangleth himſelf and ſeeketh to enſnare others with a <hi>needleſs ſcruple, viz. Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he may communicate, where the conſtitution of a thing is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful: Mr. Crofton</hi> is at no diſtance with this <hi>Remonſtrator</hi> as to the <hi>lawfulneſs of the cenſtitution of the Liturgie</hi> he will not ſtand to admit his 3. Maximes in reference to Gods worſhip</p>
            <list>
               <item>What is unuſefull is unlawfull</item>
               <item>What is unneceſſary is unlawfull</item>
               <item>What is in his general nature not commanded is unlawfull.</item>
            </list>
            <p>But they come not into his Queſtion: nor hath theſe things any thing of anſwer, to any thing pleaded by Mr. <hi>Crofton,</hi> for <hi>Communion in worſhip miniſtred by the Liturgie.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:100906:18"/>
            <p>But Sir, the <hi>conſtitution of the Liturgy</hi> being granted to be <hi>unlawful,</hi> and <hi>what ought not to be;</hi> the Queſtion yet abides, Whether the Liturgy, being an <hi>unlawfully constituted mode of ſolemn publique worſhip, be ſo far unlawful,</hi> or <hi>unlawful in that kind and quality of unlawfulneſſe, which will conſtitute a warrantable reaſon for non-communion in that worſhip of God, which is miniſtred by the ſame:</hi> Sir, all things <hi>unlawful,</hi> and relating to Gods wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, will not warrant <hi>non-communion in Gods worſhip;</hi> he muſt therefore ſpecifie an <hi>unlawfulneſſe in the Liturgy,</hi> which will be of the <hi>kind and quality</hi> which riſeth thus high, or he doth no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing; and I confeſſe, were it not for ſome fallacie in his tearms, more then (I apprehend) is in his minde, he doth this<note place="margin">Pa. 29. 35</note> to purpoſe, it is this, <hi>The Liturgy is no worſhip of God, but will-worſhip,</hi> &amp;c. no reaſon then he ſhould communicate in it as ſuch: But Sir, how ſhall we underſtand his words? they are capable of a good and true ſenſe, for the <hi>Liturgy is no worſhip of God;</hi> nor is it any <hi>will-worſhip;</hi> for, as I have be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore noted, it is not <hi>any worſhip at all,</hi> but a <hi>political order,</hi> at the moſt an <hi>bumane miniſterial mode</hi> relating to Gods wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip: But Sir, the whole ſcope of his Book, and bent of his ſpirit, maketh me aſſured, this ſenſe came not into his minde; but rather this, <hi>The Liturgy is not Gods worſhip, i. e. it is an</hi>
               <note place="margin">Page 30.</note> 
               <hi>unlawful conſtitution,</hi> and <hi>God is not at all worſhipped by it, or in the uſe of it;</hi> he therefore concludeth, his <hi>crime is in not joyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in prayer in ſuch a dreſs or form.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And Sir, this ſenſe maketh his words an aſſertion ſo hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid, and uncharitable, that he profeſſing himſelf an <hi>Antiſectari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an,</hi> I would (if I had once ground to ſupport my Charitie) hope he did not intend it; for Sir, this is the old notion urged by the <hi>brain-ſick Browniſts,</hi> and others repelled and repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by the old non-Conformiſts.</p>
            <p>Sir, the truth is, in this ſenſe he muſt be underſtood, or in none to this purpoſe; and then be pleaſed to obſerve the <hi>height,</hi> rather then <hi>strength</hi> of his <hi>Argument.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If the Liturgy be not <hi>Gods worſhip,</hi> (i. e.) <hi>Gods worſhip be not celebrated by the modes and forms directed in the Litur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy:</hi> it then followeth, our <hi>firſt Reformers and Marian Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs,</hi> rejoyced in, and dyed under a <hi>mode of divine worſhip,</hi> by which God <hi>could not be worſhipped:</hi> all our <hi>pious painful preachers</hi>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:100906:19"/> miniſtred by, and <hi>all the Chriſtians</hi> in the time of Queen <hi>Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth,</hi> King <hi>James,</hi> and moſt of the Reign of King CHARLES the Firſt, attended on a <hi>mode, dreſs, or form, by which God was not worſhipped:</hi> all the <hi>Miniſters</hi> who now miniſter in publick, and all the <hi>people</hi> in <hi>England</hi> who now attend the ſame, do miniſter by, and attend a <hi>mode, form, and dreſs, by which God is not worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped:</hi> and all who have been <hi>baptized,</hi> or <hi>received the Lords Supper</hi> in and by the <hi>modes, and forms directed in and by the Liturgy,</hi> have been mocked and deceived, and enjoyed <hi>no Sacraments;</hi> and then Sir, judg you whether <hi>England</hi> be not <hi>Paganized,</hi> and the <hi>Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents</hi> have not reaſon to <hi>gather Churches in England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sir, this man ſaith, his <hi>charity muſt be onely judged by God;</hi> ſure I am, he giveth men (by ſuch an aſſertion as this is), little cauſe to think he hath much; for a more notorious <hi>breach of charity,</hi> cannot befal the moſt <hi>rigid Separatiſt,</hi> the Church of <hi>England</hi> ever knew.</p>
            <p>But Sir, what reaſon doth this <hi>Remonſtrator</hi> render, why <hi>God is not worſhipped by the Liturgy?</hi> it is this, the <hi>manner</hi> (for the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he yields; and eſſential form he cannot deny, of the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip) the <hi>form and dreſs is humane:</hi> we grant it Sir, ſo is the <hi>mode and form of his ſtudied Sermon,</hi> and <hi>conceived Prayer;</hi> will he be willing we ſhould conclude <hi>God is not worſhipped by them?</hi> will he ſtand by it that the <hi>miniſterial mode of worſhip is determined by the Lord in his Word?</hi> if ſo a <hi>reading miniſtery</hi> may ſerve Gods Church, for there is no need of other miniſterial guifts; I would adviſe him to recollect his thoughts, and ſee whether he can de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, that it is <hi>Gods will,</hi> in <hi>condeſcention to mens weakneſſe,</hi> that <hi>the miniſterial mode of his worſhip, be determined, digeſted, by the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and faithfulneſſe of his Miniſters gifted and appointed to that purpoſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sir, though the Liturgy is a <hi>mode of worſhip obnoxious to excepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> and <hi>unlawful;</hi> yet it is only a <hi>miniſterial mode,</hi> whereby in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference to Prayer, <hi>right matter</hi> is requeſted from the Lord, in <hi>the Name of Chriſt,</hi> and ſo <hi>Gods worſhip</hi> doth ſubſtantially exiſt for <hi>matter<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> and <hi>eſſential form,</hi> and he is worſhipped by the ſame; nor doth it at all <hi>vitiate Gods worſhip,</hi> becauſe it is in it ſelf an <hi>humane mode and form;</hi> for Gods worſhip cannot exiſt in, and to the Church, but by a <hi>miniſterial mode and form humane,</hi> invented, digeſted, by men: And now Sir, where is our <hi>Remonſtrators in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>evitable
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:100906:19"/> neceſſity for non-communion in Gods worſhip miniſtred by the Liturgy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sir, the <hi>impoſing of this Liturgy</hi> may be in it ſelf <hi>an evil,</hi> but it doth not alter the <hi>nature of it;</hi> but that God is <hi>as truly worſhipped</hi> by it when impoſed, as when <hi>left at liberty,</hi> and <hi>his worſhip</hi> is as <hi>fully, formally,</hi> though not ſo <hi>orderly miniſtred,</hi> and <hi>existent</hi> in, and to the Church <hi>by this,</hi> as any other <hi>humane mode, form,</hi> and <hi>dreſſe whatſoever.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>One thing more I muſt not paſs without obſervation, and that is; this Antagoniſt ſaith, <hi>I know Mr.</hi> Crofton <hi>doth attribute the eſſential form of Prayer to it,</hi> (pag. 25.) <hi>which he deſcribes to be a</hi>
               <note place="margin">Page 39.</note> 
               <hi>calling upon God in the Name of Chriſt, but if he understand not by the Name of Chriſt the will of Chriſt,</hi> then <hi>I ſay it is not a right deſcription of Prayer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sir, I will aſſure him, Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> did not underſtand by the <hi>Name of Chriſt,</hi> the <hi>will of Chriſt,</hi> and yet I muſt tell him, it is but one Doctors opinion that this <hi>is not a right deſcription of Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er;</hi> he might have been pleaſed to obſerve in the ſame page, Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> determined the <hi>matter</hi> muſt be <hi>according to the will of God;</hi> and the will of Chriſt doth require ſome adjunct qualities, as <hi>gravity of expreſſion, fervency of affection,</hi> and <hi>reverence in demean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our,</hi> which come not into the definition of Prayer, as eſſential to its form; but in the <hi>Name of Chriſt,</hi> that is, for <hi>his ſake, merits,</hi> and <hi>mediation,</hi> cannot be left out<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </p>
            <p>Sir, I now leave our <hi>Remonſtrator</hi> on his <hi>Rack</hi> of <hi>doubting,</hi> praying God may ſhew him mercy; not doubting, but whatever they be to him, you ſee his <hi>doubts</hi> are <hi>not invincible</hi> to others<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi>'s argument ſtands yet firm, <hi>viz. The worſhip of God ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſting for matter and eſſential form, his own in ſubſtance, though by the Liturgy, (a defective, diſordered, unlawful mode) may not be refuſed or declined,</hi> this <hi>mode</hi> only by this reaſon becauſe it is <hi>hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane,</hi> maketh not an <hi>inevitable neceſſity of communion or ſeceſſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>2. Our Remonſtrator cannot communicate in the Lords Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, under the <hi>preſent modes and methods of miniſtration</hi> in the Church of <hi>England:</hi> and his ground is the <hi>impoſed geſture of kneeling, the ſuperſtition and corruption which attends it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sir, What <hi>ſuperſtition and corruptions<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> attend the <hi>miniſtration of the Lords Supper?</hi> in which he muſt <hi>perſonally act,</hi> ſo as to become guilty of the ſame, I ſee not; nor doth he ſpecifie any, the geſture
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:100906:20"/> of kneeling excepted: that the <hi>miniſterial mode of this Ordinance is diſordered,</hi> I can allow him, but <hi>this,</hi> as in other parts of publick worſhip, is <hi>perſonal</hi> to <hi>the Miniſter,</hi> and <hi>him onely,</hi> there is a <hi>poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility</hi> of his compoſed, reverend attendance on the Ordinance, without any <hi>perſonal acting in thoſe popular Reſponds,</hi> and <hi>Concla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations,</hi> which are directed to the people in and by the Liturgy.</p>
            <p>As to the <hi>gesture of kneeling,</hi> I do not find that Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> doth ſpeak one word for it, or that he ever adviſed any to it; I well know he doth not yield it, nor approve it: I have heard him ſay, that <hi>If he be put by the Communion in the Lords Supper, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he will not receive the Elements in that geſture, he is barred from his duty, and priviledge, by an act of violence he is driven, he doth not goe from Gods Ordinance.</hi> It is Sir, worth the enquiry, whether this <hi>profeſſed Separatiſt negative,</hi> have tendered himſelf to <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion in the Lords Supper,</hi> and tryed whether there were not a <hi>poſſibility</hi> of enjoying it without the <hi>geſture of kneeling:</hi> for Sir, <hi>ſeceſſion</hi> without <hi>all endeavours,</hi> and under <hi>any poſſibility</hi> of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion without what we conceive to be ſinful, cannot be acquit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of <hi>Schiſm</hi> or <hi>ſinful Separation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sir,</hi> I cannot but conceive this <hi>Remonſtrator</hi> to have in himſelf a faire latitude concerning the <hi>Geſture of kneeling;</hi> he ſaith, <hi>I could goe near to approve of the Gesture of kneeling, being left arbitrarie, and</hi>
               <note place="margin">Page 41.</note> 
               <hi>commended or practiſed onely as an outward badge of more then ordinary thank fullneſſe, under the reception of an extraordinary bleſſing, and not as an act of pietie, neceſſity and worſhip.</hi> Sir, the now Zealots for the <hi>Engliſh Ceremonies?</hi> will joyne iſſues with our Antagoniſt, and tell him <hi>kneeling at Sacrament is not act of worſhip, but only a reverend and pious badg<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> of more then ordinary thankfulneſſe, in reception of an extraordinary bleſſing;</hi> and will referre him for proof to the Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brick in their <hi>new booke,</hi> which doth declare <hi>kneeling is a ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, of our humble and gratefull acknowledgment of the benefits of Chriſt therein given to every Receiver?</hi> and the <hi>impoſition</hi> is juſtly capable of a diſpute; the <hi>Rubrick</hi> ſeemeth to do littte more than commend this Geſture, onely directing the Miniſter to <hi>deliver the Elements to the people all meekly kneeling;</hi> and the <hi>le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gality</hi> of the <hi>Canon,</hi> by him quoted is <hi>juſtly queſtioned;</hi> ſo that his reaſons on which he could <hi>go neere to approve the Geſture,</hi> ſeems to be ſo cleare, that we may wonder he ſhould not <hi>communicate in the Lords Supper,</hi> much more that he ſhould flie ſo high as to
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:100906:20"/> conclude <hi>Poiſon poſitive poyſon;</hi> his Charity is large; who can judge all that ever did; all who do now communicate in the Lords Supper, celebrated by the <hi>Service-Book,</hi> and by the <hi>Geſture of kneeling</hi> are <hi>poyſoned,</hi> expreſly <hi>kild by poyſon,</hi> this Charity will better become a <hi>totall and poſitive Separatiſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Our Remonſtrator having (as he conceived aſſigned) a ſufficient warrant for his confeſſed <hi>ſeparation;</hi> in what he ſeemeth to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to <hi>Mr.</hi> Croftons 2d<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and chief Conſideration; proceedeth to conſider ſome others, his next aſſault is on <hi>Mr. Croftons</hi> argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment from the <hi>high places in Iſrael,</hi> the <hi>high places were not taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, but the people went thither to worſhip; yet I find not that any God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fearing Iſraelite, who loathed thoſe reliques of Idolatry, ever barred them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Page 43.</note> 
               <hi>becauſe thereof, from Gods Altar and worſhip.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sir,</hi> I cannot but obſerve what a fair leap our Antagoniſt ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth; paſſing many conſiderable Arguments, urged as moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, pertinent, and regent in our Caſe, amongſt others the <hi>inſtance in the ſons of Eli,</hi> who failed in the <hi>Miniſtration of Gods worſhip,</hi> taking <hi>their owne part,</hi> before they had <hi>burnt the fatt,</hi> according to Gods own appointment; and <hi>not contented with the portion God had allotted to them,</hi> they <hi>tooke by violence what came next hand;</hi> inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that the people of the Lord <hi>loathed,</hi> yet never durſt <hi>leave the offerings of the Lord;</hi> this <hi>diſorder in the Miniſteriall mode of worſhip;</hi> runs higher then that of the <hi>Engliſh Liturgy?</hi> yet the <hi>ſin</hi> is not charged on the <hi>people;</hi> but this, and arguments of the like nature, are not worth the obſervation of our <hi>humble Remonſtrator?</hi> but be it ſo, let us conſider his batteries againſt <hi>Mr.</hi> Croftons plead from the <hi>high places in Iſrael.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Page 44<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. He tells us the <hi>retention of Jewiſh Ceremonies in the Chriſtian Church, is (God knowes) a juſt cauſe of complaint,</hi> did <hi>Mr</hi> Crofton e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver deny it?</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Reduction of them after ſacred and ſolemne expulſion is more grei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous,</hi> who denies it? what reaſon doth <hi>Mr</hi> Crofton give for his <hi>and ſhall we not complain?</hi> whoſe <hi>complaints for retrogradation of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation,</hi> have been more <hi>audible</hi> and <hi>affectionate</hi> then <hi>Mr</hi> Crof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tons? who hath more <hi>preſſed</hi> or <hi>provoked</hi> the <hi>Complaints of Gods Iſrael?</hi> and ſhall we cry to him; <hi>what and ſhall we not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Croftons alledged Caſe of the Iſraelites high places,</hi> (he ſaith) <hi>is infinitely wide of ours, Sir,</hi> it muſt be ours according to his <hi>wide
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:100906:21"/> miſtakes?</hi> for according to Mr. Croftons <hi>cloſe argumentation,</hi> it is very <hi>neer,</hi> and <hi>pertinent;</hi> the objection <hi>M.</hi> Crofton doth obviate by the <hi>Iſraelites high places,</hi> he hath indeed tranſcribed; but not once regarded, or conſidered? (<hi>viz) do men complaine of ſome Roman Rites retained? let them conſider the high places</hi> in <hi>Iſrael:</hi> what is the <hi>forme,</hi> and <hi>force</hi> of this analogicall argument? <hi>Roman Rites</hi> reteined, is <hi>unlawful matter ſuper-added to Gods worſhip?</hi> which <hi>ſubstantially exiſteth with the ſame; the high places</hi> were <hi>unlawfull matter ſuper<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> added to Gods Temple</hi> and <hi>Altar, which ſubſiſted with the ſame,</hi> the <hi>Iſraelites left not Gods Altar,</hi> becauſe of the <hi>ſuper<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> added matter of the high places;</hi> nor may Chriſtians leave <hi>Gods true worſhip,</hi> becauſe of the <hi>ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>added matter of Roman Rites:</hi> Sir, are not theſe caſes now infinite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wide? but we will weigh the diſtance he obſerveth.</p>
            <p n="1">1. He ſaith <hi>the high places were retained;</hi> our <hi>Roman Rites re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored:</hi> what then <hi>reſtoration</hi> may aggravate the evil, but doth it change the nature of the corruption; <hi>high places and Roman Rites</hi> whether <hi>retained</hi> or <hi>reſtored,</hi> are only evils ſuperadded to Gods <hi>Altar</hi> and <hi>worſhip,</hi> with which theſe doe truly formally exiſt, may and muſt bee attended; the relapſe of a Church reformed doth <hi>adde to its</hi> guilt, but not <hi>abſtract its being;</hi> returne of expelled evils do much more provoke God but not <hi>vitiate the ſubject</hi> his ordinance to which it is ſuperadded; <hi>reſtoration</hi> of corruption maketh ſin ſink deeper in the Church, or ſubject of ſuch reſtoration, but it is the <hi>qulle of the Corruption</hi> muſt ſinke into and ſubvert the worſhip of God to which it is affixed, ſo as to vitiate and deſtroy the ſame.</p>
            <p n="2">2. He ſaith the <hi>Iſraelites were confined to Gods Altar in a certain place;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Page 45.</note> and Mr. Crofton ſaith Chriſtians are <hi>confined to Gods worſhip in certain aſſemblies;</hi> true conſtituted Churches, ſuch as our Antago<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſt yieldeth <hi>Englands</hi> Congregations to be; Mr. Crofton de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nieth not <hi>local liberty,</hi> or the place of worſhip to be the <hi>matter of indifferencie;</hi> the man is miſtaken, locallity never became a To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pick of any force to Mr. Crofton he ſaith to a true Church, a lawfully conſtituted Chriſtian aſſembly, <hi>meet, aſſemble where you will and can,</hi> that which he ſaith againſt the looſe affections of ſome Chriſtians, apt to wander, is, <hi>forſake not the Aſſembling of your ſelves together, as the manner of ſome is:</hi> let Chriſts flock lie <hi>where it will or can,</hi> all particular members muſt <hi>keep Company with them;</hi> and have good reaſon before they refuſe it; Chriſts <hi>true aſſemblies</hi>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:100906:21"/> are to Chriſtians, what the fixed place, and altar was to the Jews.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>The high places were at most but Idolatrous places, but our worſhip is ſuperſtitions worſhip:</hi> and into this runs his fourth note of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, and diſparity in this Analogy, <hi>the Iſraelites worſhip was good,</hi> and <hi>place bad,</hi> but our <hi>place is only good and our worſhip is bad:</hi> No marvell Sir, if Maſter <hi>Croftons</hi> inference be to him a <hi>Non-ſequitur:</hi> but Sir, This Charity is againe the fruite of his <hi>ſeparation,</hi> and will carry him beyond the negative part of it; how? <hi>our worſhip ſuperſtitious?</hi> our <hi>worſhip bad?</hi> this cannot be admitted; who is the <hi>object of it,</hi> is it not God in Chriſt? what is the <hi>matter of it,</hi> it is not things inſtituted, appointed by the Lord him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, Word, Prayer, Sacraments? what is the form which giveth the <hi>eſſe</hi> to it? is it not what God determined, that his Word be read, preached, that he be called upon in the Name of Chriſt for things according to his will; that the ſymballs by him deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined, be given and received as ſignificant, ſealing memorials, of the death, bodie, and blood of Chriſt? is not this the ſubſtance of the worſhip miniſtred in the Engliſh Church, and much of it by the Engliſh Liturgy? is this ſuperſtitious worſhip? bad worſhip?</p>
            <p>Had our Remonſtrator ſaid, the <hi>Miniſterial mode of Gods worſhip by the Liturgy</hi> had been bad, <hi>diſordered,</hi> and not without ſome mixtures of <hi>ſuperſtition;</hi> he had not had Mr, <hi>Crofton</hi> for his Antagoniſt; but this <hi>vitiateth</hi> not its ſubject; <hi>entreth not into</hi> the worſhip; ſo as to make it <hi>ſuperſtitious worſhip,</hi> bad <hi>worſhip,</hi> the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip hereby exiſteth truly, fully, formally, <hi>Gods worſhip</hi> though not ſo comfortable, not ſo profitable to Gods people, as a better and more orderly mode for Miniſtration; but this will not do his work, his <hi>inevitable neceſſity</hi> faileth; his <hi>ſeparation</hi> appeareth ſinfull, a <hi>ſchiſme</hi> unleſſe he confound the <hi>worſhip</hi> and <hi>Miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial mode,</hi> ſo as to make the worſhip <hi>bad, ſuperſtitious,</hi> and not <hi>Gods worſhip.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sir, before we paſs this part of our <hi>Remonſtrators</hi> Anſwer, I cannot but obſerve he is at a loſſe for what he pleads againſt: he crieth, <hi>What doth Mr.</hi> Crofton <hi>plead for?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Page 46</note>
            </p>
            <p>Alas man, that ſhould have been known before now, and at the beginning of your Debate; it might have ſaved you this la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour and time; What ſaith he, <hi>Is it my preſence in the Church at the time of Divine Service?</hi> yes it is: but not as his large Conſcience, can yield it, in an <hi>Idol Temple,</hi> at the <hi>Maſſe,</hi> or <hi>Turkiſh Alchoran;</hi>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:100906:22"/> which I am ſure Mr. <hi>Crofton,</hi> or any good underſtanding Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian could not yield: nor will his <hi>neceſſity to avoid poenal Lawes,</hi> or to <hi>bear a good Sermon</hi> juſtifie his ſo doing: no matter what Religion is publickly profeſſed, this man is ſecured from ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, for he (<hi>to ſave his Eſtate</hi>) can foot it with a Church-Papiſt, to a <hi>Popiſh Maſſe,</hi> or <hi>Proteſtant Service;</hi> and if <hi>preſence in the Idol Temple in the time of Idol Worſhip</hi> may be made the Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cter by a poenal Law, you ſhall never know him for <hi>a Chriſtian;</hi> if this neceſſitie would have been ſufficient, we ſhould have had a much ſhorter Catalogue of <hi>Martyrs,</hi> both under Pagan, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Papal power, then by Gods grace we have for our encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>But Sir, that he and others may certainly know what Mr <hi>Crofton</hi> pleadeth for; I will tell him, It is for this Chriſtian, care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful carriage on Gods Sabbath. It is <hi>a preſence</hi> in the ſolemn pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Aſſembly from the <hi>firſt to the laſt</hi> of their approach to God, <hi>out of Conſcience</hi> to begin and end the <hi>holy Convocation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A preſence</hi> with a <hi>mind informed,</hi> a <hi>judgment convinced,</hi> that this Aſſembly is <hi>Gods Church,</hi> in which Gods <hi>true Worſhip</hi> is <hi>truly cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brated.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A preſence</hi> with an heart affected with, and afflicted for the <hi>ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peradded Rites,</hi> which are affixed to Gods Worſhip, and the <hi>ſinful defective, diſordered mode,</hi> by which Gods Worſhip is mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A preſence</hi> with a Conſcience convinced theſe <hi>Corruptions are e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil,</hi> but not ſo evil as to <hi>deſtroy Gods Worſhip;</hi> but that the ſame doth (even by this ſinful mode) exiſt <hi>truly, formally Gods Worſhip;</hi> ſo as to uſe Gods Ordinance with delight, though grieved, bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dened by the <hi>diſorder of the miniſtration.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A preſence</hi> with a mind perſwaded the <hi>modifying of Gods Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip</hi> is the <hi>perſonal duty</hi> of the Miniſter, and ſo the <hi>defects and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orders</hi> therefore his <hi>perſonal ſin;</hi> ſo as that theſe may be the good mans <hi>burden,</hi> (being bound to mourn for other mens ſin, eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in what ſo much concerneth his own profit, and edification) but cannot be his <hi>ſin,</hi> who hath thereof no <hi>publique judgment</hi> by ſpeciallity of Office.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A preſence</hi> with a mind ſoberly vigilant over its own <hi>perſonal actings,</hi> ſo as to decline all <hi>popular reſponds, conclamations,</hi> and <hi>va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riation</hi> of <hi>Geſtures,</hi> and the like actions, which are unduly requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:100906:22"/> from him; ſo as to contain himſelf under ſuch diſorder in a <hi>compoſed ſilence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A preſence</hi> with a ſerious apprehenſion <hi>of God</hi> to whom the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice is di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ected; and the <hi>nature of the Worſhip</hi> miniſtred; ſo as with <hi>reverence</hi> to attend the Word read, and Prayers pronounced, though in <hi>parts, parcels,</hi> with unfit <hi>intermixtures, abruptions, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>breviations,</hi> and <hi>pauſes;</hi> ſo as to ſigh and ſpeak out an <hi>affectionate Amen,</hi> the whole, the only <hi>vocal part</hi> of the people in publique Worſhip.</p>
            <p>Sir, this is the <hi>preſence</hi> which Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> pleadeth for, as that which <hi>true Religion,</hi> and <hi>good order</hi> doth require, and direct, whilſt Chriſtians cannot enjoy Gods Worſhip in communion with his Church, by a miniſterial mode<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> more <hi>regular, perfect,</hi> and <hi>profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,</hi> digeſted by the <hi>perſonal abilities</hi> of each Miniſtrator.</p>
            <p>Sir, our <hi>Remonſtrator</hi> proceedeth to another of Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi>'s <hi>Conſiderations,</hi> and that he accounted his ſecond, but in the order of Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi>'s Book it is the third, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>Communion with the Church under<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> many and great corruptions, is not inconſiſtent with zeal, care and contest for Reformation.<bibl>Page 46, 47, 48.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>What he ſaith to this is partly true, That <hi>endeavours of Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation are a duty;</hi> that <hi>Connivance is an argument of Affection<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion an argument of Connivance;</hi> the <hi>negative part of Reformation, bindeth ad ſemper,</hi> and the like; all which Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> hath aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted, and amplyfied in his <hi>Plea:</hi> nor doth he detract or deny them; but theſe are <hi>generals,</hi> in the application of which our <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monstrator</hi> followeth the miſtake of the Queſtion, which hath miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guided him throughout his whole <hi>Remonstrance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Herein, like an acute Diſputant, he correcteth Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi>'s ſtate of the Queſtion, and profoundly tells us; <hi>Mr.</hi> Crofton<note place="margin">Page 47.</note> 
               <hi>had done well to have ſtated the Question aright, de eccleſia reformanda, &amp; de eccleſia reformata:</hi> Good Mr. <hi>Remonſtrator</hi> may not <hi>eccleſia eadem,</hi> be <hi>eodem tempora reformata, &amp; reformanda,</hi> what if a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Church <hi>relapſe</hi> into ſome of tee <hi>ſame Corruptions,</hi> which were <hi>ſolemnly expelled,</hi> is ſhe not <hi>eccleſia reformanda?</hi> is there no cure for her but <hi>ruine?</hi> and no carriage towards her, but to <hi>relin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſh</hi> and run from her? doth the <hi>Criſis</hi> of the Queſtion lye in her <hi>relapſe,</hi> and <hi>retrogradation</hi> in Reformation, and into the <hi>ſame cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions</hi>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:100906:23"/> which had been <hi>ſolemnly expelled;</hi> or in the <hi>quality</hi> and <hi>na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the corruptions</hi> which are returned into her? if her <hi>relapſe</hi> be into <hi>extrinſecal, circumſtantial corruptions,</hi> which notwithſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the <hi>ſubſtance</hi> of Gods Worſhip, and <hi>ſalvability</hi> of Gods peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple is continued, and ſecured, is not the Queſtion then plain, <hi>Whether communion with her relapſed into ſuch corruptions be not conſistent with zeal, care and conteſt for<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Reformation?</hi> and who will deny that? but if the relapſe into <hi>intrinſecal, and ſubſtantial corruptions</hi> which <hi>vitiate</hi> the ſubject, and <hi>deſtroy</hi> Gods Worſhip, and the <hi>ſalvability</hi> of Gods people; then indeed <hi>ſeparation,</hi> not only <hi>negative,</hi> but <hi>poſitive</hi> is a duty.</p>
            <p>But Sir, I wiſh the <hi>Remonſtrator</hi> may review Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi>'s Plea, and ſee that he doth conſider the Engliſh Church <hi>reformed, relap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed,</hi> and to <hi>be reformed,</hi> and pray he will conſider <hi>relapſe,</hi> and <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gradation</hi> is the aggravation of the Church's ſin, and provoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Reformers zeal; but, the <hi>quale of the corruptions,</hi> whether firſt introduced, or after ſolemn expulſion returned into it, is that which muſt direct, and determine <hi>Communion</hi> or <hi>Separation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But Sir, no ſtate of the Queſtion doth, nor indeed can be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected to ſuite his miſ-guided zeal, but what is ſquare to his <hi>mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaken judgment;</hi> he therefore here again c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ieth out of <hi>Communion in Corruption; Communion in the Liturgy;</hi> and according to the uncharitable fancy of the old brain-ſick <hi>Browniſts,</hi> and moſt rigid <hi>Separatiſts,</hi> his Dialect is, <hi>It is no Worſhip; God is not Worſhipped;</hi> it is <hi>a going back into Egypt;</hi> it is <hi>poyſon; I. will dye of famine rather then of poiſon;</hi> and the like, which is every where ſcattered up and down his <hi>Remonſtrance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To all this I know, <hi>Mr. Crofton</hi> will grant to him <hi>Communion in the Corruptions, Communion in the Liturgy</hi> is not <hi>conſiſtent with endeavours for reformation:</hi> But Sir, herein lyeth the difference between <hi>Mr. Crofton</hi> and this Antagoniſt, the one maketh cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions the direct immediate object of <hi>Communion;</hi> the other doth make <hi>Gods worſhip ſubſtantially for matter and forme,</hi> only Miniſtred by <hi>ſuch a corrupt mode,</hi> and with ſuch and ſuch <hi>corrupt appendants converſant</hi> about it, which enter not into it, the <hi>object of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion; Mr. Crofton</hi> ſaith, we muſt communicate in Gods wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip <hi>hereby Ministred;</hi> and the <hi>Remonſtrator</hi> ſaith, we do <hi>commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate in the coru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptions, in the</hi> Liturgy; <hi>Mr Crofton</hi> is ſo farre from pleading for <hi>Communion in the Liturgy,</hi> that he ſaith <hi>Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:100906:23"/> cannot without ſin uſe it,</hi> for they are Judges? and ſtand char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged with the Miniſterial mode of worſhip; and <hi>non-miniſtration</hi> by it is the leaſt Art of <hi>reformation;</hi> nor doth he plead for, or juſtifie the perſonal actings of the people, in thoſe <hi>popular Reſponds,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Read h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion not Separati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> 
               <hi>Conclamations, and groundleſſe change of Geſture,</hi> which is their part of Communion in it as a Liturgy; nay, ſo farre is <hi>Mr.</hi> Crof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>om preſſing <hi>Communion in the Liturgy, that he</hi> maketh <hi>atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance on Gods worſhip miniſtred</hi> by the form of the reſult <hi>neceſſity;</hi> and blameth the ſame in a caſe of <hi>choice, or liberty,</hi> to enjoy Gods worſhip in a more orderly and regular mode.</p>
            <p>If Sir, the <hi>Remonſtrator</hi> will not take the queſtion as it is ſtated, the caſe of Conſcience as it ſtands, and came cloſe to the criſis of the Controverſie, if he will not diſtinguiſh between his foode, and the unclean veſſel, and ill-favored carving which doth tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit it to him, if he will not differ between a <hi>neceſſity</hi> of feeding in <hi>ſuch veſſels</hi> on good wholſome food, <hi>ill-favouredly carved<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> and <hi>mangled,</hi> or ſtarving, and a liberty and choice of a better and more orderly <hi>miniſtration;</hi> he may be afraid of and all his dayes fight with his ſhadow; for he fighteth not with <hi>Mr</hi> Crofton whoſe queſtion is manifeſt in, and through his whole booke, to be about neceſſitated Communion in <hi>Gods worſhip in ſuch an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitting Miniſterial mode.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sir, Mr Crofton would not have any reforming Chriſtian <hi>goe back,</hi> or <hi>retreat</hi> from the degree of Reformation they have at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained: but this is the caſe, and private Chriſtians duty; the <hi>forum</hi> of the Church viſible (at leaſt the particular to which they relate) is changeable, and changed, yet confiſteth of ſuch who are <hi>true and lawfull</hi> though it may be not pious) <hi>Ministers of the Goſpell,</hi> theſe are Judges; and do aſſume, &amp; by their office <hi>impoſe</hi> on the Church a <hi>Miniſterial mode</hi> of Gods worſhip, which is <hi>rude, diſorderly,</hi> and was <hi>ſolemnely expelled;</hi> the people and particular members do <hi>nau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeate,</hi> are burdened at this <hi>mode,</hi> yet cannot deny Gods worſhip doth <hi>truly, formally</hi> and <hi>ſalvably exiſt</hi> in and by it, they have no <hi>publique Judgement</hi> of, nor <hi>moral power</hi> to correct this <hi>mode,</hi> may paſſively attend, &amp; perſonally act their part in <hi>Gods publick worſhip,</hi> without any <hi>perſonal acting</hi> in the <hi>Ministeriall mode;</hi> muſt they in this caſe not keepe their places? but recede from Communion, and reſolve to live without ſolemne publique worſhip, not knowing how or where to have it better Miniſtred? Sir I would
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:100906:24"/> intreat our <hi>Remonſtrator</hi> to let his future diſcourſe turne on the <hi>binge</hi> of the controverſy; or his anſwer will be rejected as a groundleſſe and forced creaking, not more unpleaſant then un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable.</p>
            <p>Our <hi>Remonſtrator</hi> doth ſuggeſt ſomthing from the Oath, called the <hi>Solemn League and Covenant,</hi> (of which he ſpeaketh in ſuch tearms, as ſpeak little of wit, or honeſty, and leſſe Scotch zeal) as making for his fancy <hi>argumentum ad hominem at leaſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sir, we all know that <hi>Oath</hi> is become a <hi>Noli me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tangere,</hi> I muſt not plead for it, but this I will tell you, Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> who hath reaſon, (having ſtudied and diſputed it, and deeply ſuffered for it) to underſtand that <hi>Oath</hi> will undertake to plead his principle, as that to which that <hi>Oath</hi> doth oblige; I will in his behalf note theſe three things conſiderable in this Caſe, to which that <hi>Oath</hi> doth bind: they are theſe.</p>
            <p n="1">1. It obligeth to <hi>Reformation in Worſhip,</hi> which ſuppoſeth worſhip doth <hi>fully and formally exist,</hi> defiled with ſome <hi>extrinſecal corruptions</hi> which muſt be removed, expelled; but ſtill the <hi>ſubject</hi> muſt be owned and ſecured; not declined or refuſed whilſt we conſcientiouſly attend <hi>Worſhip,</hi> we muſt carefully endeavour it may be as <hi>pure,</hi> as it is <hi>true.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> This Reformation muſt be endeavoured <hi>in our places and Calling by lawfull meanes,</hi> but the private capacity of particular members of the Church, diſpoſe them to endeavours by no means but what reſult from the <hi>Judgement of Charity, viz.</hi> obſerving o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mens ſin, they muſt grieve for it; <hi>admoniſh</hi> even <hi>Elies</hi> ſons to <hi>forbear it; Complaine</hi> to God and ſuperiors, humbly petitioning <hi>a Reformation</hi> by their publique authority; and in caſe of choice, and liberty, attending Gods worſhip miniſtred in a better <hi>Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterial mode;</hi> but in caſe of neceſſity, rather then not attend Gods worſhip truly, ſalvably exiſting, their place doth binde them to attendance on it in this <hi>mode?</hi> but with a greived, burdened, complaining, ſupplicating ſpirit; that this evill may be reformed, bringing their <hi>offerings</hi> to the Lord, whilſt they <hi>loath</hi> and rebuke, are greived for, and complaine againſt the <hi>Prophane Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration</hi> of the ſons of <hi>Elie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. This Reformation muſt conſiſt with reall ſincere indeavours to extirpate <hi>ſchiſme,</hi> as well as <hi>ſuperſtition;</hi> Mr Crofton hath well cautioned us, that the Divell doth labour to <hi>reforme</hi> the one, by
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:100906:24"/> 
               <hi>running</hi> as upon the other ſin; but the grace of God keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth<note place="margin">Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> us in an <hi>equal oppoſition</hi> to both: Now<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> unwarrantable ſeceſſion from Gods worſhip, this very <hi>Remonſtrator</hi> grants is a <hi>ſeparation,</hi> and a ſin, and although it be but <hi>negative and</hi>
               <note place="margin">P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ge 46.</note> 
               <hi>partial,</hi> yet it hath in it the formality of <hi>Schiſme:</hi> our <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrators inevitable neceſſity</hi> we have found before doth varliſh; on his miſtake he muſt aſſign another, and that from the <hi>nature</hi> and <hi>quality</hi> of corruption, or <hi>impoſſibility of communion in Gods true worſhip,</hi> without <hi>communion in the miniſterial mode,</hi> which is evident may be abſtracted from the <hi>worſhip;</hi> and Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> doth affirme is a <hi>perſonal act,</hi> though of a <hi>publique Officer</hi> to a publique end</p>
            <p>Sir, the whole of what the <hi>Remonſtrator</hi> ſaith in this point of <hi>Reformation</hi> is this: <hi>Mr. Crofton</hi> ſaith, <hi>the matter,</hi> (and he ſhould have added the eſſential form, for ſo <hi>Mr. Crofton</hi> ſaith)<note place="margin">Page 48<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> 
               <hi>is good, but the outward mode is bad, and to be reformed;</hi> this our Remonſtrator very often and with great humility calleth <hi>Mr. Crofton's recocta Crambe;</hi> and yet as often as it is boyled by <hi>Mr. Crofton,</hi> it hath no good connection in this mans ſtomack; all the nurture he draws from it, is but like <hi>Scotch Keal,</hi> which turneth into winde and vapour.</p>
            <p>Sir, our Remonſtrator muſt yet have this <hi>crambe recocta,</hi> it is the <hi>Criſis</hi> of this Controverſie, till it be digeſted, this Caſe of Conſcience cannot be reſolved; Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> grants, that the whole <hi>frame and conſtitution of the Liturgy is to be refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, removed;</hi> but he deemeth it to be <hi>adulterate worſhip</hi> and affirmeth it to be only a <hi>deſective, diſorderly miniſterial mode of Gods true worſhip,</hi> of which the people hath not <hi>pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique judgment,</hi> and by which they may enjoy <hi>Gods Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances,</hi> capable of operation to their end, without any <hi>communion in this mode,</hi> which is <hi>perſonal</hi> in a <hi>publique Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficer</hi> to a publique end, and muſt therefore be <hi>reformed</hi> by the endeavours of all in <hi>their places,</hi> and without unwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantable <hi>ſeceſſion, negative ſeparation, formal Schiſm,</hi> and ſo a ſinne.</p>
            <p>They who have made a <hi>Schiſm</hi> between <hi>Paſtors</hi> and <hi>People</hi> by an act of violence, and exaction of what muſt not be yielded, muſt be <hi>pittyed and prayed for,</hi> but not
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:100906:25"/> paid in their own Coyn by us, or repelled by our <hi>perſonal ſin</hi> and <hi>Schiſm:</hi> I deſire to ſerve God, but God keep me from ſerving him by my ſin; where <hi>ſin</hi> is Gods inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>judgment</hi> (his ſtrange work) is his buſineſſe, and the fire is uſually prepared for ſuch <hi>Inſtruments,</hi> when their work is done.</p>
            <p>Our <hi>Remonſtrator</hi> ſtumble<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h on another <hi>Sentence</hi> of Mr. <hi>Crofton's Plea,</hi> for indeed he no where taketh the <hi>ſcote,</hi> or underſtandeth the <hi>form and force</hi> of any Argument; he<note place="margin">Page. 5.</note> faith Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> ſaith, <hi>I cannot without trembling conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the circumciſed Sects in the Church of</hi> Corinth, (<hi>Coloſſe</hi> he meant) <hi>are charged to have left the head, by leaving the body:</hi> This our Antagoniſt ſaith is a <hi>ſtrange Argument,</hi> unleſſe his <hi>non-Communicants be proved to be circumciſed Sects,</hi> and <hi>guilty of ſuch corruptions as will amount to a not holding the head.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here Sir, our <hi>Remonſtrator</hi> (who taketh no Argument right) is run out into another miſtake; as if Mr <hi>Crofton</hi> did allude to the <hi>circumciſed Sects</hi> for their <hi>corruption,</hi> who alludeth to them for their <hi>ſeparation,</hi> not holding <hi>in the body,</hi> and ſo <hi>not holding the head;</hi> be the corruptions of any Church or People what they will; a <hi>ſeparation,</hi> and <hi>unwarrantable ſeparation from Gods true Church</hi> is a <hi>leav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the body,</hi> and ſo not <hi>holding the head;</hi> the eſtate of which is ſo <hi>dreadful,</hi> that every good man cannot but <hi>tremble</hi> to ſee any in the leaſt appearance thereof, motion, or tendency thereunto.</p>
            <p>Sir, What our <hi>Remonſtrator</hi> doth urge in caſe of ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dal is no contradiction in <hi>theſe</hi> to Mr. <hi>Crofton,</hi> in what he hath aſſerted: but in <hi>hypotheſi</hi> he hath run on his old miſtake, <hi>Is communion in the Liturgy a poſitive duty?</hi> is<note place="margin">Page. 53.</note> his Quaerie: Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> ſaith, <hi>No;</hi> but <hi>communion in Gods worſhip miniſtred by the Liturgy,</hi> is a <hi>poſitive duty</hi> to ſuch who have no choice, and cannot enjoy Gods worſhip in communion with Gods Church Catholique viſible, in <hi>a better miniſterial mode and order.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Saith he, is not the <hi>Liturgy indifferent?</hi> Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> faith, <hi>No;</hi> it is not: not as the Biſhop told him, becauſe
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:100906:25"/> 
               <hi>impoſed,</hi> but becauſe a <hi>formal poſitive evil,</hi> but yet it is not an evil of that <hi>nature and quality,</hi> as to intercept the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſpenſible duty of communion in Gods true worſhip mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred by it, when we have no choice.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Saith he, <hi>Will not ſcandal accrue by Mr.</hi> Crofton'<hi>s communion, as well as conformity in the Liturgy;</hi> Mr <hi>Crof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> ſaith, <hi>It will;</hi> but he denieth <hi>all communion in the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgy;</hi> and his <hi>non-conformity</hi> is the act of <hi>non communion</hi> in his capacity, as a Miniſter; his <hi>non-perſonal acting</hi> in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny the popular <hi>Reſponds, Conclamations,</hi> and <hi>groundleſſe va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riation of Geſtures,</hi> is the evidence of his <hi>non-communion,</hi> as a Member of the Church.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> is ſenſible, men, and good men, are, and will be ſcandalized by his <hi>communion in Gods worſhip, mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred by this mode;</hi> but this is by <hi>accident,</hi> not from the <hi>nature of his act,</hi> but from the <hi>ignorance</hi> and <hi>weakneſſe</hi> of thoſe who take it, and therefore are no bar to his duty; indeed weak, though good men may well ſtumble, when this man of Learning hath no more brains, then to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found <hi>communion in Gods worſhip miniſtred by the Liturgy,</hi> with <hi>communion in the Liturgy,</hi> and ſo conclude Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> a <hi>Mecaenas and Advocate for the Liturgy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sir, That which is the great ſtick, and ſtumble with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, though this acute Diſputant doth not urge any thing againſt it, is this principle which ſome men (whoſe judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſhould be better) is pleaſed to call <hi>proprium Degma</hi> to himſelf, (<hi>viz.) I can communicate in Gods worſhip mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred in that humane miniſterial mode and order, by which I cannot adminiſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sir, The general reaſon of this his reſolution, is the <hi>mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dification of Gods worſhip in, and to the Church, is the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonal act of the Miniſter:</hi> If Sir, this act be <hi>perſonal,</hi> the Miniſter may not be <hi>impoſed on,</hi> all ſins in the <hi>miniſterial mode,</hi> are <hi>his, who miniſtreth;</hi> and they extend not to the Church, unleſſe by accident through ſome defect of their own: Sir, this general might be amplyfied by theſe parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>A Miniſter by his Office stands charged to modifie Gods wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:100906:26"/> by his miniſterial gifts, and perſonal abilities;</hi> he may not therefore be <hi>impoſed on,</hi> be the modes impoſed never ſo good; he may as well admit <hi>compoſed Sermons,</hi> as <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed Prayers,</hi> and forms for Adminiſtration of Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Every Miniſter hath a publique judgment of the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterial mode by which he miniſtreth the worſhip of God,</hi> and doth <hi>qua</hi> Miniſter, as a publique Officer, receive this, and reject that; ſo that if he receive a mode <hi>defective</hi> and <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orderly,</hi> the ſin becometh his.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Every Miniſter is perſonally active in the miniſterial mode by which he miniſtreth, ſo that he mangleth Scripture,</hi> and doth perſonally act all that diſorder which is in it.</p>
            <p>Theſe things are well illuſtrated by Mr. <hi>Croftons</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſion to the <hi>Recorder of the Citie,</hi> or <hi>Speaker in Parliament,</hi> and ſhew good reaſon why he cannot conforme to, Miniſter by ſuch and ſuch a miniſterial mode.</p>
            <p>But his miniſtry (as to exerciſe) being ſuperſeded, and he reſolved into the ſtate and capacity of a <hi>private member</hi> of the Church, conſidereth,</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>This miniſterial mode is evil, but not ſuch an evil as vitiateth the ſubject;</hi> Gods worſhip doth <hi>truly, formally, ſalvably,</hi> (though not <hi>comfortably</hi> or ſo <hi>proſitably</hi> as by an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other) exiſt in, and to the Church by it, and I cannot have Gods Ordinances in communion with Gods Church without it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>In this miniſterial mode, the members of the Church are purely paſſive,</hi> they according to their duty, aſſemble to worſhip God; the Miniſter charged with the <hi>bumane mode,</hi> doth aſſume a Miniſter by this, the which the members of the Church do not <hi>adviſe</hi> or <hi>chooſe,</hi> nor any way <hi>act in,</hi> but com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſedly attend the <hi>worſhip of God</hi> hereby miniſtred unto them, and exhibited for their <hi>Amen:</hi> ſo that the ſin is <hi>perſonal,</hi> not publique and common, no way derived to me, unleſſe by my neglect to mourn for this, as any other ſin in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:100906:26"/>3. Though this mode of worſhip do direct ſome acts to be done by the people, yet <hi>I am Master and Judg of my own action,</hi> and can <hi>with-hold,</hi> and <hi>refuſe it,</hi> ſo that in the whole miniſtration I <hi>act not,</hi> but in my <hi>Amen</hi> to the prayer <hi>thus modified,</hi> and my <hi>attention</hi> to the worſhip <hi>thus miniſtred,</hi> and the ſinful mode is by, and to the Miniſter, and him alone.</p>
            <p>Sir, Let not any infer, that on theſe grounds we may attend a <hi>Maſſe</hi> and be innocent: For Sir, the corruptions in a Maſſe are ſuch as <hi>vitiate the Subject,</hi> and deſtroy the worſhip of God.</p>
            <p n="1">1. It is celebrated in <hi>an unknown tongue,</hi> and ſo doth not exhibit any worſhip; it is to the people, <hi>vox &amp; prete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rea nihil,</hi> it is a frivolus objection, <hi>I underſtand Latine,</hi> when the <hi>Church,</hi> who underſtandeth it not, is the <hi>ſubject</hi> of the worſhip to be done to God, the Queſtion is of <hi>pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique communion,</hi> not my private and perſonal adoration.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Maſſe doth pray <hi>to the Saints,</hi> a wrong object; in <hi>the name of the Saints,</hi> a wrong ground, for ſome <hi>unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful things;</hi> wrong matter of prayer, Gods worſhip is not herein exiſtent, but deſtroyed.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Maſſe maketh the <hi>Sacraments Sacrifices for the quick and dead;</hi> tranſubſtantiateth the Elements, and ſo chang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the nature of the Ordinance in the very nature and <hi>eſſe</hi> thereof.</p>
            <p>We are Sir, at laſt, arrived at the laſt quarrel our <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrator</hi> picketh at Mr. <hi>Croftons</hi> Plea, in which he is exactly ſquare to his miſtaken ſelf.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mr.</hi> Crofton <hi>ſaith, I am not without the caution and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct of ſober, godly, learned promoters, and purſuers of a perfect and compleat Reformation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To this the <hi>Remonſtrator</hi> ſaith, <hi>It is ſtrange Mr. Crofton</hi>
               <note place="margin">Page 54.</note> 
               <hi>ſhould argue from communion amongſt diſtinct Churches, againſt the non-communion of preſent members of one and the ſame Church, ſince that is a communion not by participitati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> and joint fellowſhip.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How Sir, not by <hi>participitation and joint fellowſhip?</hi> that is ſtrange; though not by <hi>conſtant participitation perſonal, by their individual members,</hi> yet by <hi>joint fellowſhip</hi> in the ſame ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:100906:27"/> worſhip, and <hi>occaſional perticipation</hi> reciprocally, each with other, by their <hi>particular members caſt into this or that Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try:</hi> Sir, can other Reformed Churches hold communion with <hi>England,</hi> if her worſhip be <hi>no worſhip of God? will-wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, Scripture-bitten, will-worſhip?</hi> Moreover, Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved<note place="margin">Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion not Separati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> the <hi>Reformed Churches diſowned not,</hi> on occaſion <hi>declined not, never adviſed their travelling members to decline communion with England,</hi> her Liturgy notwithſtanding, they ſure con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded<note place="margin">Page 43.</note> Gods worſhip was therby miniſtred.</p>
            <p>Again, this Remonſtrator telleth us, Mr. <hi>Croftons inſtance in the primitive Non-conformiſts, is wide of that of the modern;</hi> it is true, and Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> tells us in his Plea, <hi>He was ſenſible of it,</hi> they <hi>adminiſtred by this miniſterial mode,</hi> which Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> ſaith, <hi>He can better excuſe than juſtifie;</hi> yet the diſtance is not<note place="margin">Page 44.</note> ſo great, as this mans wild fancie doth dream; they were un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ſame <hi>corruptions</hi> for <hi>kind,</hi> which are returned upon us; yet <hi>Hilderſham, Ball, Nichols, Hind,</hi> and others maintained the <hi>duty of communion in Gods worſhip, under, in, and by them,</hi> againſt <hi>Brown, Barrow,</hi> and other <hi>Rigid Separatiſts,</hi> who urged this mans grand Argument, it was not <hi>Gods worſhip,</hi> and it was <hi>will-worſhip:</hi> I know our <hi>Remonſtrator</hi> diſowns relation to theſe men, and their Sects, yet ſheltereth himſelf under their <hi>ſhield,</hi> and fighteth with no weapon, but what was forged on their <hi>Anvil,</hi> and in their <hi>Shop,</hi> only he addeth ours is an <hi>eſtate of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lapſe;</hi> that is indeed true, and aggravateth our ſin, but alter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not the <hi>nature</hi> and <hi>quale of the corruptions;</hi> if theſe cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions returned do <hi>vitiate the ſubject,</hi> and <hi>deſtroy Gods wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip,</hi> they did ſo when <hi>firſt inovated,</hi> or <hi>continued</hi> in the firſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation; for as I have before urged it is only the <hi>quality,</hi> not the <hi>degree</hi> of the evil muſt <hi>vitiate Gods worſhip,</hi> to make it <hi>poyſon,</hi> expreſs <hi>poyſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sir, I have done with this <hi>Remonſtrator,</hi> when I have told him Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> is a <hi>Peter,</hi> who can receive the <hi>rebukes of a brother Paul;</hi> but the rebukes of a Zeal, miſtaking matter of fact, doth only retort on the Cenſurer, with a <hi>what doth your arguing re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove?</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>I am Sir, <signed>Your Obliged Friend, R. S.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <date>Febr. 13. 1662.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb n="43" facs="tcp:100906:27"/>
            <head>POSTSCRIPT.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Worthy Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>YOu cannot but have heard, that Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> in his late tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vels, had a <hi>Paper</hi> taken out of his pocket, it was a rough Draught of his high-way thoughts which he committed to paper, to communicate to a <hi>now Conformiſt,</hi> a good friend of his; him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf had not another Copy, for whilst it was in his hand, it was never tranſcribed by himſelf, or any other; I having, with ſome difficulty, procured a Copy thereof (from one relating to the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman who took it from Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi>) have preſumed to ſend it you, that if you think good, you may make it publique, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by capacitate our conforming Clergy, to reſolve (if they can) one of the <hi>great Scruples</hi> which barreth Mr. <hi>Croftons Conformity and Miniſtration</hi> by a Liturgy; however, the world will ſee what a <hi>Mecaenas and Advocate he is for Liturgies;</hi> This <hi>Paper</hi> being ſince his <hi>Plea for Communion.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Vale.</salute>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
